<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Oeconomica sacra, or, A parænetical discourse of marriage together with some particular remarks on the marriage of Isaac and Rebecca.</title>
            <author>J. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P62</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13165492</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13165492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 431:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Oeconomica sacra, or, A parænetical discourse of marriage together with some particular remarks on the marriage of Isaac and Rebecca.</title>
                  <author>J. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 102, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: J.P.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [14].</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Pages 95-96 are tightly bound in filmed copy. Pages 80-end photographed from Cambridge University Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Oeconomica Sacra:</hi> OR A Paraenetical Diſcourſe OF
MARRIAGE: Together with ſome PARTICULAR REMARKS ON THE <hi>Marriage</hi> OF
<hi>ISAAC</hi> and <hi>REBECCA.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Faelices ter &amp; amplius,</l> 
               <l>Quos irrupta tenet copula; nec ullis</l> 
               <l>Divulſus quaerimoniis</l> 
               <l>Supraema citius ſolvit amor die.</l> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horace.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Saluſbury,</hi> at the
<hi>Atlas</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable JAMES Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi>
VISCOUNT <hi>CRANEB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN,</hi> Baron <hi>Caecill</hi> of
<hi>Eſſenden.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Doctrine of Vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Vegetation, as it is the Act of an
Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God, ſo 'tis a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious <pb facs="tcp:98231:3"/> Myſtery to Man: And
as the Divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Legitimacy in proſecuting the
Succeſſion of natural Cauſes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of Corporeal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, was
a clear Indicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Divine goodneſs, and a publick <hi>Manifeſto</hi> to
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge Mankind in Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal embraces; as Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to thoſe wiſe and
honourable purpoſes, for which Marriage was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; ſo the Pravity and
Corruption of the humane Nature, is viſible in thoſe notorious deviations
from the Primitive Sanction: And the eager purſuite of <pb facs="tcp:98231:3"/> unlawful
and deſtructive pleaſures doth wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the appointed Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum; and
this violence of appetite continuing, the mind is dealt withall, and prepared
to an Aſſent, and reaſon proſelyted to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of
paſſion.</p>
            <p>The fatal effects of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication and Adulteries, are too plainly
apparent in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying bodily health; the ruine of Families and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
the debauching the generality of Mankind, the Production of a miſerable and
obſcure Progeny, the Atarchy and Confuſion in Government, the loſs of 
<pb facs="tcp:98231:4"/> Property in the World, the want of Education and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of
Parents, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolition of Religion and Devotion; and in ſhort, the
Deſtruction of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: all which are ſufficient Puniſhments in
themſelves. Did I ſay Puniſhments? I muſt only call them Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,
Proaemial to Eternal Torments.</p>
            <p>How will the wiſer Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then condemn ſuch bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial and
irrational Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces! they valued themſelves highly, in hopes of their
<hi>Elyſium,</hi> and Life to come, and diſdained the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
any thing incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous <pb facs="tcp:98231:4"/> to ſuch expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The Holy
Reſolution of <hi>Seneca</hi> ſtands upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; <hi>Faciam omnia tanquam
Deus videret:</hi> And hence the Philoſopher ſo much preferred his
contemplative,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> before his practick
felicity; and the Poet <hi>Claudian</hi> tells us, That Nature, meaning the God
of Nature, aſſigns happineſs to all men.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Natura Beatis,</l> 
               <l>Omnibus eſſe dedit, ſi quis cognoverit uti.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now who can be ſo fooliſh, and act <hi>Antipodes</hi> to his
own Reaſon; as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate <pb facs="tcp:98231:5"/> into Senſuality and
uncleanneſs, which inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pulls on Everlaſting Miſery? Whereas
nothing can more advance the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature to its primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Dignity and
Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, than Obedience to the Supream Law-giver; and nothing can gratifie
the Senſes of a thinking man, but what is licenc't by the bounty of
Heaven.</p>
            <p>God having thus admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably conſulted the good of Mankind, who
would not accept of ſuch Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Invitations, when Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Enjoyments are
not only lawful, but indulged, <pb facs="tcp:98231:5"/> and man made an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to
propagate Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and conferr a Religious Education to his Children,
preſerve Honour and Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, Peace, and Concord, good Government and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum in the World, and all thoſe <hi>Placentia</hi>'s and Contents of
Marriage, are but praelibations of celeſtial Joys hereafter.</p>
            <p>And your Lordſhips ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condeſcenſion to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial
Obligation, hath encouraged this Dedication; that as your Honour is a Noble
Advocate for Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, ſo I have great hopes to preſume, that your
Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <pb facs="tcp:98231:6"/> will protect this piece againſt the licentious
hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of a depraved Age; when Marriage is decry'd, as a reſtraint upon
Liberty, and the beaten path of our wiſer Anceſtors utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honour's Moſt Humble, and Faithfully
Devoted Servant,</hi> J. P.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>E Muſeo meo Londini, </hi>

                  <date>
                     <hi>die</hi>Maii, 25. 1685.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>French</hi> firſt intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the ſolemnity of a
Preface, and others as well as they have abuſed it to a great deal of Vanity;
and out of pretended modeſty have large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decry'd their own Works, and 
<pb facs="tcp:98231:7"/> the Imperfection of their pieces: Yet after all, to publiſh them
to the World, is no better than to adventure upon a Crime, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt open
Conviction and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment.</p>
            <p>I would not be here miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued, but ſubmit to the
favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable cenſure of the Judicious; and ſhall have as low a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
for my own Works as any man.</p>
            <p>And as this Treatiſe was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by my accidental read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the twenty fourth Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and compoſed for my private
Recreation at vacant hours (but by the importunity of ſome Friends now made
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick) ſo 'tis recommended to <pb facs="tcp:98231:7"/> your vacant time and leiſure
to peruſe it; and if it give you but a ſmall diverſion, and a little
benefit, conſider, that even that time which was beſtowed on reading of it,
might have been worſe ſpent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:8"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 64. <hi>line</hi> 19. <hi>for</hi> Imperial
<hi>read</hi> Empyrean.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98231:8"/>
            <head>OF <hi>Marriage.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is a Maxim in Nature to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Happineſs and Society,<note place="margin">Naturae ſemper in meliorem tendit.</note> and to aim at
Improvement and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; this was at firſt declared by the God of Nature,
<hi>It is not good for man to be alone;</hi> and hath ſince been practiſed
by mankind as the <hi>ſine quâ non,</hi> without which the Species
could not be preſerved; becauſe the all-wiſe God having inveſted the
hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature with a <hi>Potentia,</hi> and Organical helps for generation;
and alſo given thoſe reſpective Produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions an inherent faculty of life
and vegetation, he was not further pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to propagate mankind by
Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as he did the Angels, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the perfecting their firſt
Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; he was not pleaſed to Create, <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98231:9"/> but form the Woman
<hi>ex materia praeexiſtente,</hi> of the Rib of <hi>Adam;</hi> which alſo
implies, that as there was an Identity of <hi>Materia prima,</hi> for
conſtituting Organical Bodies, ſo there is alſo an innate and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
affection and ſympathy reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal: Now it pleaſed God to tye theſe two
pieces of Nature toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the ſacred bonds and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Ordinance of
<hi>Matrimony,</hi> whereby God did not only ſupply <hi>Adam</hi> with a meet
help for Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, but alſo ſuperadded the Comfort and enjoyment of
Society, the Woman reſembling the Man in nature, ſhape, body and mind, and
there being nothing wanting to <hi>Adam</hi> for the Conſummation of his
Happineſs but a Wife, he was made Lord over the Creatures, Heir of of the
World, and ſeated in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; and God providing him a fit Companion, hath
abundantly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed what he wanted; and man ever ſince retains ſuch
Principles and Inclinations ſuitable to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Nature, which
by Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers is ſtyled, previous Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98231:9"/>
or Aptitudes in matter to attain and ſeek after; which brings us to
diſcourſe of <hi>Marriage,</hi> which God Inſtituted for his own Glory,
the good of Mankind, and benefit of Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marriage</hi> being the ſubject of which we are to treat, we
will firſt conſider it in its <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in
its <hi>Effects.</hi> And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Its <hi>Appointment</hi> is Divine.<note place="margin">A
priori.</note> After God had ſaid, <hi>It is not good for man to be
alone;</hi> it follows, <hi>Let us make a meet help for him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for man is by nature a ſociable
Creature, and deſirous of Company, as a learned Commentator on the place
tells us. An individual makes no Society,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Nec jucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduo, nec utile ſpeciei.
<hi>Piſcator</hi> in loc.</p> 
                  <p>Tanquam alter ipſe ſpecie &amp; formâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniens.
<hi>Rivet</hi> in loc.</p>
               </note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſerviceable to its Species;
therefore God gave man a Wife, as another ſelf, of the ſame Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and
Figure with himſelf; than which nothing could be ſo meet an help, both for
Society and Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Iſſue, which was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary
for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mankind. And in the ſecond Chapter of
<hi>Geneſis</hi> we have an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Womans formation, 
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98231:10"/> that ſhe was formed of the Rib of <hi>Adam,</hi> and
preſented to him, and thereupon ſhe becomes <hi>aliquid ipſius,</hi>
ſomething of him, if not <hi>alter idem,</hi> another ſame, which the
School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men declare for; that ſhe being formed out of a Rib, there was both
Fleſh and Nerves, which makes her an <hi>alter ipſe:</hi> And ſhe being
after the ſimilitude of man, he might the more affect and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of her;
for humane Nature is taken with ſimiles, and we are pleaſed with the reflex
of our ſelves, and like <hi>Narciſſus</hi> even dote upon identical
dilations: the ſacred Phraſe runs thus,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Deus crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem marem &amp; faemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam. <hi>Vulg.
lat.</hi>
                  </p> 
                  <p>Matrimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um humano generi im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tribuit.
<hi>Neviſanus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>God created man male and female.</hi>
There being then an inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of conſtituted matter, that the love of
Society and Conjugal affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions might be homogenial and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal: Whereas
if God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a Friend only, the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had been deficient, neither
could the Species be preſerved without a Genus: but the Ordination of God,
and current of Nature have made them individually one, God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented her to
man as a ſecond ſelf. <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98231:10"/> Nature and Religion, Law and
Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy ſtrictly oblige them to this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oeconomy: This was viſible
in <hi>Adam</hi>'s Apprehenſion and Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of it, as we read 23, and
24. verſes; <hi>This is now bone of my bone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen.
2.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>and fleſh of my fleſh:</hi> And in the 24. verſe we
have the conſequents of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſacred Inſtitution; <hi>Therefore
ſhall a man leave Father and Mother, and cleave to his Wife, and they two
ſhall be one fleſh:</hi> That is not,<note place="margin">Non loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur de
car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectû con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugali. <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Fagius,</hi> in
loc.</note> as one obſerves, ſpoken of fleſhly Luſting, but out of
Conjugal Affections and Love to his Wife, who reſembles the two branches in
<hi>Ezekiels</hi> hand; encloſed in one bark, and cloſing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether make
but one fleſh, as being a Society of the moſt endeared Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and
Friendſhip.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matrimonii ſymbolum.</hi> Ezek. 24.26.
Micah 7.5. Prov. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>Be thou
raviſht always in her Love:</hi> in the Original it is, <hi>Erre thou alwayes
in her love; velut extra ſis ut rerum aliarum obliviſcare;</hi> which
ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a very earneſt affection, and a reſpect immeaſurable: And
our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf, when he lived on earth, was pleaſed to
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Marriage with his perſonal <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98231:11"/> attendance; and to put
the greater accent and honour on ſo ſacred a Solemnity, was further
pleaſed, to the admiration of all Spectators, to work his firſt Miracle
thereat, by turning Water into Wine; which tacitly implies that Marriage brings
honour and perfection to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature,<note place="margin">Faelix
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitas quae ad meliora tendit.</note> which was ſhaddow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out by
the melioration of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and was a clear ſignification and approbation of
thoſe lawful delights and entertainments, which were ſuitable and proper to
the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: this Nuptial tye is Recorded in Heaven, Solemnized on Earth,
and Confirmed by the mutual gages of two united individuals. This Love is the
Harmony,<note place="margin">Nil habet natura me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius quam ut poſſis, neque
praeſtantius quam ut ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſervare plures. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero.</hi>
               </note> the
Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Genius, and very Soul of Nature; this true Friendſhip is the
Zodiack wherein the Sun of Truth, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and hearty Affections,
inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably compleat the whole cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of motion and influence; and is the
Guardian and tutelar Angel of Society, to which <hi>Quarles</hi> alludes in his
deſcription of Conjugal Love.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98231:11"/> 
               <l>They were ſo one, that none could juſtly ſay,</l> 
               <l>Which of them rul'd, or whether did obey;</l> 
               <l>He rul'd, becauſe ſhe would obey, yet ſhe</l> 
               <l>In ſo obeying rul'd as well as he.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And as it was inſtituted for Gods glory, and preſervation of
Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſo to preſerve inviolate the Laws of God, by avoiding and
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting Fornication,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.14. Mark 10.19. Heb.
13.3.</note> which is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by God in ſeveral places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>We can ſtill deſcribe and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the primitive rectitude
of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, though the fall hath maimed our perfection, and impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
thoſe glorious Ideas we had at firſt, and diſpoſed us to ſin, and
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viations: At firſt the action of ſenſe was appointed to touch the
affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo preſent it primarily to the Underſtanding, by whoſe
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the Paſſions were ſubordinate and ſubject to its inclinations,
and as its Deputies in the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98231:12"/> of ſuch
Duties and Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for the Benefit, Service and Happineſs of the
humane Nature; which Underſtanding in the Soul is called an Intellectual
Lamp, which God placed for the admirable go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of his Creature; and the
School-men call it <hi>Lumen Naturae,</hi> the Light of Nature, which St.
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">St.
<hi>Chryſ.</hi> 13 Orat.</note> and tells us, that 'tis a radical and
fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental knowledge planted in the being of Man, budding and bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoming
in his firſt Principles, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and bringing forth fruit, ſpreading
it ſelf into all the fair and goodly branches of Morality, under whoſe
ſhaddow the Soul takes great delight: And tells us further, that it grows
ſpontaneouſly, ſhines out chearfully and pleaſantly; 'tis ſo
viſible, that the infant age of the World could ſpell it out, and read it
without a Teacher before <hi>Moſes</hi> was born, or <hi>Aaron</hi> wore his
Golden Bells; before there was a Prophet or Judge in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and
ſo the learned <hi>Grotius</hi> deſcribes it: The Law of Nature (ſayes
he) is a <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98231:12"/> ſtreaming out of glorious Light,<note place="margin">Jus Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale, eſt dictatum, rectae Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, actui
alicui, ex ejus conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nientia &amp; diſconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia cum ipſa Naturae
Rationali, ineſſe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem aut neceſſitatem moralem,
&amp; conſequenter ab authore naturae ipſo Deo, talem actum aut vetari, aut
praecipi. <hi>Grotius de jure Natu.</hi>
               </note> powerfully diſcovering ſuch
a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in ſome evil, as that an intellectual Eye muſt needs abhor it;
and ſuch a commanding Beauty in ſome good, as that a rational being muſt
needs be enamoured with it, and ſo plainly ſhewing that God ſtampt and
ſealed the one with his Command, and branded the other with his diſlike; to
which <hi>Plutarch</hi> very excellently alludes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This
Royal Law of Nature, ſayes he, was never ſhut up in a paper Priſon, was
never confined and limited to any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſurface, but was bravely
ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated in the Center of a rational being, alwayes keeping the Soul
Company, for its protection and direction; ruling all its Subjects (all
obedient actions) with a Golden Scepter, and cruſhing to pieces its Enemies,
that's all rebellious and evil actions. And <hi>Plato</hi> tells us, that this
Law is founded in Nature, for the maintaining, ennobling, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting
of Nature. But <hi>Tully</hi> draws a moſt lively portraicture of the 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98231:13"/> Law of Nature:<note place="margin">Eſt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vera lex
recta ratio, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruens, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſa in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans,
ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piterna, quae vocem ad officium ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendo, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tando, fraude de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreat,
quae tamen pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bos, neque fruſtra ju bet aut ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut, nec improbos ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendo,
aut vetando mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet; Hinc legi nec pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagari jas eſt, neque derogari ex hac
aliquid licet, neque tota abrogari poteſt; nec vero aut per Senatum, aut per
populum ſolvi hac lege poſſimus; neque eſt quaerendus explanator, aut
interpres ejus alius, non erat alia <hi>Roma,</hi> alia <hi>Athenis,</hi> alia
nunc, alia poſthac, ſed &amp; omnes gentes omni tempore una Lex &amp;
ſempiterna, &amp; immutabilis continebit, unuſque erit quaſi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis
Magiſter &amp; Legiſlator omnium Deus, ille legis hujus inventor,
diſceptator, lator, cui qui non parebit, ipſe ſe fugiet, &amp; naturam
hominis aſpernabitur.</note> The Law of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſayes he, is a beautiful
Law, a Law of a pure Complexion and Natural colour, of a vaſt Extent and
diffuſion; its colour and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cannot fade, it encourages men in Obedience
with a ſmile, it chides them and frowns them out of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; good men
hear the whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perings of its pleaſant voice, and obſerve the leaſt
glance of its love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eye; but wicked men ſometimes will not hear it when it
comes to them in Thunder, nor take the leaſt notice of it, though it flaſh
out in Lightning; none muſt enlarge nor diminiſh this Law, neither can the
malice of men totally deface its Beauty, neither Prince nor People, Angels nor
Men can abſolve you from it; this Law never paints its <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98231:13"/>
face, nor change its colour; it does not put on one aſpect at
<hi>Athens,</hi> and another at <hi>Rome,</hi> but looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Nations and
Perſons with an impartial eye; it ſhines upon all Ages, and Times, and
Conditions with a perpetual Light; there is but one Law-giver, he contrived and
commanded it, and none can be exempted from it, unleſs he be baniſht from
his own Eſſence, and excommunicated from humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions: Thy Law, ſayes he,<note place="margin">Tua lex, tua lex ſcripta eſt in cordibus noſtris, quam non
ulla un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam delet iniquitas.</note> is written in our hearts, which no
Iniquity can blot out. And the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Heathen braved it out in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
expreſſions; That Beauty and Goodneſs was a ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and
compenſation, that the very turpitude of evil actions is Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment enough
in it ſelf: And what an high pitch of greatneſs did <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> attain
to, when he calls Laws that were made by man, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Juſtice, and
Puniſh Vice, but <hi>Hominum infirmiorum commenta,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance for
weak men, to keep them virtuous. And <hi>Seneca</hi> divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98231:14"/> expreſt himſelf;<note place="margin">Licet ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem
Deum ignoſciturum &amp; homines ignoraturos, attamen peccare nol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ob
pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem. <hi>Sen.</hi> Vir bonus reveretur ſeipſum.</note>
If I were ſure, ſayes he, that God would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pardon me, and men
could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know of it, yet I would ſcorn to ſin for its foulneſs and
diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty. And what Chriſtian can keep pace herein, endeavouring after
ſuch original rectitude? and when he gave the world that golden Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm,
That a good man has a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for himſelf; what ſtrong emulations had
he to climb after Original Purity, and advance Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to her primitive
Dignity! how did he aim after the Image of his Maker, to preſerve that
Species of Goodneſs implanted in him, as knowing that ſins and
immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were the degenerations of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, and would debaſe him
into a Devil.</p>
            <p>Now man being a free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Creature, hath a freedome and
liberty to proſecute his own happineſs, and having taſted that forbidden
fruit, how has he as it were poyſoned himſelf and poſterity! And how hath
that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Picture of his Maker loſt its <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98231:14"/> gloſs and
beauty, and the oriency of its colours! <hi>Horreſco referens!</hi> We
tremble to relate how that ſweet harmony of his faculties, and
ſubordination of them to each other, is broken; how every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the
inferior power has diſobeyed that government and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection which the
ſuperior did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter! how hath man baſely exchanged reaſonable and
well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Paſſions for ſenſual and beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly!<note place="margin">Tanta eſt vis volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum ut &amp; ignoranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um protelet in
occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam corrumpat in diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem.
<hi>Tertul.</hi>
               </note> what crookedneſs and diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is there
fighting againſt his reaſon! what Soleciſms in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners! what
impoſtures to obliterate reaſon and original truth! and the Underſtanding
being caſt out, Paſſion hath uſurped the Chair, which judges of things,
not according to natural truth, but according to the Impreſſions of Fancy,
Pleaſure, and the dictates of corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>And this Corruption of Nature is particularly ſeen in
Incontinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: God of his great goodneſs hath given us a lawful and
honourable uſe of thoſe innate deſires, and propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98231:15"/> of nature in mutual enjoyments, <hi>ad converſationem
ſpeciei,</hi> for Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſake, but not to ſatisfie thoſe vile
affections of Luſt, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks; and forſaking the guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
of reaſon, they diſhonoured their bodies amongſt themſelves, as St.
<hi>Jude</hi> tells; which is ſtyled by the Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> 
               <hi>Morbid</hi> deſires; and the Apoſtle
tells us, that he who commits fornication ſins againſt his own Body.<note place="margin">Morbus eſt affectus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram corpori incidens.</note> As
<hi>Fernelius</hi> obſerves of diſeaſes, that they are affections of body
contrary to Nature; ſo are Adulteries and Fornications. The Poet
repreſented <hi>Agamemne, Os oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culuſque Jovi par,</hi> in his features
like <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in valour like <hi>Mars,</hi> in Wiſdom a very
<hi>Apollo</hi> himſelf: But when angry and paſſionate, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd
into a Lyon, a Tyger, a Devil. So man was created after the Divine Image, and
ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſacred obligations of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Inviolable: but by
Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Adulteries metamorphos'd into a Beaſt, a Devil; and though
the Commiſſion of Sin at firſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes corrupt Nature, yet the
viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98231:15"/> of the Divine Law, and our guilty
Conſciences, will affright and torture us. The Poet tells us, 
<q>
                  <l>Principium dulce eſt, ſed finis amoris amarus,</l> 
                  <l>Laeta venire Venus, triſtis abire ſolet.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This vultures and gnaws the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted heart, this brings
deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Soul and Body; whence proceeds ſuch <hi>Ghonorreahs</hi>
and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamations of Liver, and brings a ſuddain Cataſtrophe to life it
ſelf.<note place="margin">Suetonius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. ejus.</note> It ruined
<hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho</hi> the Emperour, Pope <hi>Sextus</hi>
the fourth: <hi>Qui diſſeſſit tabidus voluptate,</hi> as the
<hi>Hiſtorian</hi> tells us. And as <hi>Turtullian</hi> obſerves, the Body
quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fails the Mind, the Mind the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, the Deſire the Satisfaction,
and all the man. And how hath Gods Judgments purſued the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teror!<note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> 
               <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> was ſtabb'd in the
Senate-houſe, as a juſt reward of his Incontinence: And how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable was
Gods judgment upon the <hi>Levites</hi> Wife,<note place="margin">Judg. 19.20,
21.</note> that plaid the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultereſs! and we have an account 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98231:16"/> how ſhe was cut and divided into twelve pieces, and
ſent into all the Coaſts of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And it would be too tedious
to relate, what miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and deſtruction it brought to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> and
<hi>Cleopatra, Auguſtus Caeſar, Mary</hi> of <hi>Aragon, Rodolphus</hi> of
<hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardy,</hi> and others: And one wittily expreſſes it,<note place="margin">Non eſt è terris mollis ad aſtra via.</note> the
paſſage to Heaven is all the way up-hill, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Adulterer with
his rotten lungs cannot climb it up. <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength was
enervated by a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: And <hi>Solomons</hi> Wiſdom nigh extinguiſhed in
the fire of Luſt. What a blot and diſhonour was it to <hi>Amnon,</hi> and
how was his Sin ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated in the caſe of <hi>Thamar!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither does it terminate in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal deſtruction, but
affects Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, nay Kingdoms and Empires: what miſery did <hi>David</hi>
bring on himſelf and family by Adultery with <hi>Bathſheba!</hi> and how
terrible the Divine Judgment againſt him! <hi>The Sword ſhall not depart
from thine houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.10, 11, 12.</note>
               <hi>becauſe thou haſt deſpiſed the Lord, and taken the Wife of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah
the Hittite:</hi> and it muſt needs prick him <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98231:16"/> to the
Heart, when <hi>Nathan</hi> ſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically expoſtulates the caſe, and
ſumms up Gods great goodneſs to him, after he had killed
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 7, 8, 9.</note> and done evil in the
ſight of the Lord: And we find that Idleneſs was a great ſtep to this
Sin. <hi>David</hi> walking on the top of his Houſe, ſaw that Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful
Woman: The ſoul wanting the Salutiferous food of buſineſs, preys upon
evils; as the Poet tells us of <hi>Aegiſtus</hi> his Adultery, 
<q>
                  <l>Quaeritur Aegiſtus quomodo ſit factus Adulter,</l> 
                  <l>In promptu cauſa eſt, Deſidioſus erat.</l>
               </q> It was
Idleneſs adminiſtred the occaſion of his Sin.</p>
            <p>We would therefore more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially recommend Imployment and
Buſineſs, as a great preſervative againſt thoſe Sins: they preſerve
the mind againſt thoſe ſenſual ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations and Syren
Inchantments, and fortifie the ſoul againſt thoſe fatal Poyſons that
kill us in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and ſo preſerve it invulnera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from the Arrows
of a <hi>Lais</hi> or <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98231:17"/> 
               <hi>Cleopatra;</hi> obſtruct
thoſe <hi>peccata in deliciis</hi> which otherwiſe might ſtorm and
conquer our beſt reſolutions; and like a Coat of Male which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
the body, ſo buſineſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the mind from thoſe fatal
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantations;<note place="margin">Homines ni hil agendo malè agere
diſcunt.</note> but if we give up our ſelves to Idleneſs, a hundred to
one but ſome evil attacks us. As a match takes fire, ſo Luſt overtakes
Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: hence the Poets repreſent all Shepheards laſcivious and
effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, becauſe generally Idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: ſo <hi>Theophraſtus</hi>
defines it, <hi>Otioſi animi affectus.</hi> And <hi>Seneca</hi> is in the
right when he tells us,<note place="margin">Juventâ gignitur, Luxû
nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritur, feriis alitur otio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inter lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta fortunae bona.</note> Youth
begets it, riot maintains it, Idleneſs nouriſhes and continues it. How
luſtful and effiminate was <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades, Sardanapalus, Nero</hi> and
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers! Whereupon St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, That wherever Security and
Idleneſs prevails, there wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and luſt reigns.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bicunque ſecuritas, ibi libido
domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur.</note>And that it affects Kingdoms and States, we find it in the
caſe of <hi>Sodom.</hi> God rained down Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven, and
deſtroyed the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> as <hi>Pererius</hi> 
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98231:17"/>
notes on the Place;<note place="margin">Ex eo quod relatione ad Deum ſub nomine
Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maton di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur, val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de male, &amp; peccatores ſignificatur eo
contra jus naturae valde pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>câſſe. <hi>Pere. in Locum.</hi>
               </note>
Giving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over to Fornication, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after ſtrange fleſh,
they ſinned againſt the light of Nature: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Paſſion and
Indignation of <hi>Lactantius</hi> is commendable, when he ſayes, That no
Indignation againſt this Sin of <hi>Sodom</hi> is enough: and as their
puniſhment was by fire, ſo it was ſuitable to the Nature of their Sin,
and burning Luſts, as <hi>Gregory</hi> expreſſeth it. There was Luſting
without meaſure, and exceſs of riot;<note place="margin">Sulphure
ſignificatus &amp; punitus fuit peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum foetor, igne libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ardor.
<hi>Greg. in locum.</hi>
               </note> and as their Sins were of a crying and
aggravating Nature, ſo the execution of their puniſhment was by Fire, which
is accounted moſt afflictive to Senſe, and a ſuitable puniſhment for
the greateſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And this fire was a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous fire; the Text
ſays, <hi>The Lord rained Fire and Brimſtone, from the Lord: Pererius</hi>
renders it, <hi>E Noſtris,</hi> it came not from the Strength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
cauſes, but immediately from God himſelf. God wrought a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to
puniſh thoſe <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and to put a difference between the
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Generation of fire and Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98231:18"/> produced from
natural cauſes,<note place="margin">His verbis ſignificatur quod praeter
naturalem, rerum cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendo ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quos ad
dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferentiam enim natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralium cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali ordine occurrenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ad
ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerandum ſulphur &amp; ignem, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctum eſt illud, A Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova.</note> it
is ſuperadded in the Text, <hi>in terminis, è Jehovah,</hi> from the
Lord; and this is the ſence of the beſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, as <hi>Toſtatus,
Calvin, Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus, Paraeus</hi> and <hi>Rivet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what but the Adultery of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> with
<hi>Hellena,</hi> occaſioned the <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> War, the Ruin of that
famous Kingdom, the Death of <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Hellena,</hi> and King
<hi>Priamas</hi> himſelf! And <hi>Sextus Tarquinius</hi> for the Rape of
<hi>Lucretia,</hi> (for which ſhe ſlew her ſelf,) was both expelled his
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſlain by the <hi>Sabines;</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> very
properly Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed their Funeral Rites at the Gate of the Temple of
<hi>Venus,</hi> to let the World know, that Luſt and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence was an
Haſtener and Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Death. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> relates ſad Stories
of the Impurities of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> and <hi>Clemens
Alexandrinus</hi> of the <hi>Carpocratians:</hi> therefore let us all remember
that Poetical Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition; 
<q>
                  <l>Corpus, opes, animam, famam, vim, lumina, Scortum</l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98231:18"/>Debilitat, perdit, necat, aufert, eripit,
orbat.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And let us ſeriouſly conſider the Royal Obſervation of the
Wiſeſt King:<note place="margin">Prov. 7.25, <hi>and</hi> 26.—</note>
               <hi>She hath caſt down many wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yea, many ſtrong men have been
ſlain by her: Her houſe is the way to Hell, going down to the Chambers of
Death.</hi> We will only juſt touch at the manner of the Nuptial
Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo proceed to conſider the Effects of Marriage. The
Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents Solemnized thoſe Sacred Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations with ſuch Care, that God
himſelf might be an apparent Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that holy Covenant; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Nations have obſerved ſeveral ſorts of Ceremonies; and we may ſuppoſe
them wiſely and judiciouſly inſtituted, as the Repreſentatives of that
great Myſtery. The <hi>Hebrews</hi> had firſt their Betrothings, then their
Conjugal Rites: There was a diſtance of time between their Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſals,
and the Conſummation; which is obſervable from the Anſwer of
<hi>Rebecca</hi>'s Mother unto <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servant, that ſhe might
remain <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98231:19"/> with her at leaſt ten dayes after the
Eſpouſals: Several Friends aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted at this Ceremony; and they had
an <hi>Epithalamium,</hi> or Nuptial Song ſung by ſome particular Friends,
ſtyled, the <hi>Children of the Bride-Chamber:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat.
9.15.</note> And that this <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneal</hi> Song was no other than a Form of
Bleſſing pronounced on the new Married Couple, is thus deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by
<hi>Genebrand:</hi> 
               <q>The Chief of thoſe Companions taketh a Cup, and Bleſſeth
it, ſaying; <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord our God, which created Man after his
own Image, and hath thereby prepared to himſelf an everlaſting Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
Bleſſed be thou, O Lord our God, who haſt created Joy and Gladneſs, the
Bridegroom and the Bride, Charity and brotherly Love, Rejoycing and Pleaſure,
Peace and Society: I beſeech thee, O Lord, let there be ſuddenly heard in
the Cityes of</hi> Judah, <hi>and Streets of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>the voice
of Joy and Gladneſs, the voice of the Bridegroom and the Bride; the voice of
Exultation in the Bride-Chamber is ſweeter than any Feaſt, and Children
ſweeter than the ſweetneſs of a Song.</hi>
               </q> And he drinks to 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98231:19"/> the Married Couple;—From which our vulgar Cuſtom
of <hi>wiſhing them Joy</hi> and Happineſs proceeds.—They kept their
Marriage Feaſt ſeven dayes;<note place="margin">Judg. 14.10. <hi>and</hi>
11.—</note> which ſpace of time they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for mourning, whence
came that <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Proverb, <hi>Septem ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivium, ſeptem ad
Luctum:</hi> And there was a Wedding Ring given to the Bride, with this
Inſcription, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zal Tob,</hi> which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> call the Planet
<hi>Jupiter,</hi> according to <hi>Munſter,</hi> which they thought of great
Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Vertue for Generation. And the Subjection and Modeſty of Women
in thoſe days is obſervable: When the Wife was firſt preſented to her
Husband, ſhe covered her ſelf with a Vail: Thus did <hi>Rebecca,</hi> when
ſhe eſpyed <hi>Iſaac</hi> coming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, ſhe took a Vail,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.65.</note> and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered her ſelf. Now as the
<hi>Hebrews</hi> pray'd unto God, ſo other Nations had their particular
Auſpicious Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and forms of Invocations; as, at <hi>Athens,
Hymeneus;</hi> and at <hi>Rome, Thalaſſius;</hi> that the Marriage might be
happy and fortunate: And they adorned one Finger of the left Hand 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98231:20"/> with a Ring, as a Symbol of their great Love to their
Husbands; and they were wont to be carryed into their Husbands Houſes, to
intimate, that they loſt their ſollicited Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity not voluntarily. We
will not trouble you with the ſeveral Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms which were accommodated to
Magnificence and Splendour of the Nuptials, the Sports of Gladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators, and
Preparations of Paſtime for the People, which <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> calls,
the <hi>Delightful Product of Riches:</hi> And for our modern Cuſtoms herein,
and modes of Celebration, we paſs them over, to haſten to the Effects of
Marriage.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A poſteriori.</note>Secondly, We come to
conſider the <hi>Effects</hi> of Marriage: And we are not about
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbraticam Cauſam,</hi> need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs things; but our deſign is to
bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon the Sacred and Noble Effects of Marriage.<note place="margin">Finis dat
amabilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mediis.</note> 'Tis the End and good Conſequence of things that
gives the greater Luſtre and Lovelineſs to the Cauſes.—Man being a
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregable Creature, by reaſon of his Speech, the <hi>Communative Organ of
Society,</hi> as <hi>Cicero</hi> tells us;—Man <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98231:20"/>
delights in the Company of his own <hi>Species,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pares
cum paribus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregantur. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </note> and the
Similitude of their Natures hath conſtituted a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Alliance amongſt
themſelves. And <hi>Toſtatus</hi> tells us, That that was the Original of
Civil Communication, for the mutual Preſervation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: The happy
Effects of it were ſeen in the ſeveral Families and Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciations of
the firſt Age:—The firſt Oeconomies and Inſtitutions for the
Government of Mankind, was the bleſſed Effects of Marriage.— Here the
admirable wiſdom of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſhined out, and here the
Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Proclamation took place; <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God on High, on Earth
Peace, good Will towards Men:</hi> For, no ſooner was Man created for God's
Glory, but a meet help aſſigned him; and the next thing in Nature after
Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration follows Preſervation, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination, and Government, as a
Pattern to Succeeding Ages, for the Government of God's Church and People in
the World. Now Self-love being an inſeperable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty to all Beings,<note place="margin">Amor ſui.</note> we muſt needs delight in the Preſervation
of our <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98231:21"/> own Eſſence, for the Unity we find in our
ſelves: And when in Nature, or Habit, we find the Similitude and Character of
our ſelves, the Beams and Powers of our Wills and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions do extend and
dilate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon thoſe Objects reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Now a
Repreſentation is made,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In <hi>Subſtance;</hi> as the Husband and Wife are
<hi>One Fleſh,</hi> and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the Branches of their Parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>Accidents,</hi> or <hi>Qualities;</hi> as one Man
is like to another, either in the Dimenſions of Body, Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of
Phyſiognomy, or mental En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments;—all which prompts Nature to mutual
Exerciſes of Love and Courteſie. And this natural Civility and Providence
extends to other Creatures as well as Man: <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> reports of the
Affection of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants to their Young: That the Pelican, if the Naturalliſts
may be credited, when her young Ones have been bitten, feeds them with her own
Blood, for their Recovery, (which a <hi>Portugal</hi> Prince made Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blematical
to expreſs his Love to his Subjects;) and other Creatures ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98231:21"/> this Affection, according to <hi>Elian:</hi> Nay, the
moſt cruel of Beaſts, the Tyger, if <hi>Statius</hi> be not miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: 
<q>
                  <l>—Sic aſpera Tigris</l> 
                  <l>Foetibus abreptis Scythico deſerta ſub Antro</l> 
                  <l>Accubat, &amp; lepidi lambit veſtigia lecti.<note place="margin">Lib. 10.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, what Regiment this affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on does obtain upon the whole
Claſſes of vegetable nature, is pleaſant to obſerve: in the Vine and
Elm how great a ſympathy! the Olive and the Mirtle embrace each other. What a
ſtory is related of two Palm trees in <hi>Italy</hi> by <hi>Jovianus
Pontanus,</hi> in his Poems! Naturaliſts allow them Male and Female, and that
they will not grow out of each others ſight. The Poet <hi>Claudian</hi>
deſcribes the Paſſion of <hi>Vegetables,</hi> thus, 
<q>
                  <l>Vivunt in venerem frondes, omniſque viciſſim,</l> 
                  <l>Foelix arbor amat, nutat &amp; mutua Palma;</l> 
                  <l>Faedera, populco ſuſpirat populus ictu.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98231:22"/>But in Mankind how much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is this
affection, and who can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to deſcribe the extent of Conjugal Love!
Man admires her as his meet help; ſhe was built in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe:</hi>
Nature hath given her pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Elements in her Compoſition, and ſweetned her
Countenance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sternneſs of a Male Aſpect, and hath intruſted
her with the Conception, Production and Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Poſterity. And God gave
the honour of our Redemption to the Seed of the Woman; man is more obſequious
to that Sex than his own. For a virtuous and wiſe Woman is like the
Ambaſſador of a Prince, held as a Perſon ſacred: man admires her for
that ſecret ſweetneſs that indulge and gratifie all his ſenſes at
once in his Converſation with her; and is ſenſible of the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
ſo excellent a Creature without himſelf, and of the honour he receives by
help of Propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and parity of natural Union: ſhe is the high Chamberlain
of his Soul, <hi>Privado</hi> of his Senſes, and with the <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98231:22"/> charms of her figure,<note place="margin">In totâ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerum
natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ nihil for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, nihil auguſtius, nihil
praeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſius cujus vires hinc facile intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liguntur.
<hi>Socrates.</hi>
               </note> feature and relation, can perſwade him into more
than all the intermitted retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of a Maſculine friend.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ab talem uxorem qui praeſtentiſſima forma,</l> 
               <l>Nil mortale refert.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>But it would be too tedious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Examples of Conjugal
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; we paſs over the Love of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> to
their Wives;<note place="margin">Ezek. 24.16.</note> of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> whoſe
Wife was called <hi>the delight of his Eyes;</hi> the Vulgar Latin is,
<hi>Deſiderium Oculorum tuorum. Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> died in the
kiſſes of his Wife <hi>Livia. Conjugii noſtri mea mor, vive &amp;
vale.</hi> We paſs over the affections of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and
<hi>Placilla</hi> his Queen, of <hi>Seneca</hi> and <hi>Paulina,
Manſolus</hi> and <hi>Artemeſia:</hi> and it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of one that
ordered to be writ on his Tomb, That he had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with his Dear Wife forty
three years eight months, and never fell out. What a bleſſed
<hi>Amneſtia</hi> does this noble Conſtitution ſettle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men! And
the Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98231:23"/> of a good Wife ſweetens Life, and
baniſhes vexation; to whom we may tell our diſcontents, and have them
leſſened, and our joyes, and have them multiplyed: and he that hath a good
Wiſe, hath two ſelves, and poſſeſſes all his faculties double.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Homer</hi> brings in <hi>Paris</hi> kiſſing
<hi>Hellena</hi> after ten years Marriage, proteſting as much affection as if
but newly conjoyned. Like the Old man in <hi>Auſonius,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor vivamus quod vivimus, &amp; moriamur</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Servantes nomen ſumpſimus in thalamo;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nec ferat ulla dies ut commutemur in aevo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quin tibi ſum Juvenis tuque puella mihi.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <lg>
                     <l>Dear Wife let's live in love, and dye together,</l>
                     <l>As heretofore we have in all good will;</l>
                     <l>Let no day change or alter our affections,</l>
                     <l>But let's be young to one another ſtill.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98231:23"/>Much like the ſaying of <hi>Solomon, And
rejoice with the Wife of thy Youth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 5.19.</note>
               <hi>let her be as the loving Hind, and the pleaſant Roe; let her Breaſts
ſatisfie thee at all times, and be thou raviſhed alwayes with her
Love.</hi> Here is a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick and charming quality, a powerful and occult
motive; and though he rule his Wife as head, yet ſhe again commands his
Heart; no happineſs like it, <hi>placens <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor,</hi> a ſweet Wife.</p>
            <q>Omnis Amor magnus, ſed aperto in conjuga major:</q>
            <p>No Love ſo ſtrong as this Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Love, they being but one
fleſh are unanimous, and <hi>Gerion</hi>-like,<note place="margin">Amicitiae
ſymbolum.</note> 
               <hi>Coaleſcere in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num,</hi> and have but one Heart in
two Bodies.</p>
            <q>Corporibus geminis Spiritus unus erat.</q>
            <p>And ſo continue in mutual Love, affection and endearments to
each other; according as the Poet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonates a Loving Husband: 
<q>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98231:24"/> 
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Propertius.</hi> Lib. 2.</note>Et me ab
amore tuo deducet nulla ſenectus,</l> 
                  <l>Sive ego Tythonus ſive ego Neſtor ero.</l> 
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>No age ſhall part my Love from thee, ſweet
Wife,</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thô I live</hi> Neſtors, <hi>or</hi> Tythonus
<hi>life.</hi>
                  </l> 
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>è diverſo,</hi> the Woman al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath a
great ſenſe of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal obligations; ſhe admires her Husband as
her Head and Protector, and under God a <hi>Melior Natura,</hi> an Auſpicious
Genius, and Tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Angel, concern'd for her happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and conſulting
all the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable methods for her Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Comfort: And the Care,
Diligence and Induſtry of a good Husband, for the Preſervation and
Happineſs of her, and hers, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends him the more to her Love and moſt
endeared affections. She cannot but adore the Divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that when her
Parents are dead, and her Friends fail her, that ſhe hath a ſecond Self,
who is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy if ſhe be miſerable; and under <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98231:24"/> God her
happineſs in this World depends immediately on the Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Sobriety,
Diligence and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of her Husband. Man and Wife ſhould reſemble the
Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims in the Temple, which looked on each other; ſo they ſhould love
and admire each other, and meet half way in the joint Proſecution of both
their good. The Apoſtle exhorts <hi>Husbands to love their Wives as Chriſt
loved the Church:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.25. Col. 3.18.</note> And
<hi>Wives to ſubmit themſelves to their Huſbands, as it is fit in the
Lord, and win them by their ſweet Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</hi> And the Wiſe
man,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.1.</note> in his deſcription of a loving and
induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wife; ſays, <hi>She will do him good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not evil all
her dayes;</hi> And goes on deſcanting on the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar parts of her good
houſewifery: And in the 28 <hi>verſe,</hi> Pronounces his bleſſing on
her;<note place="margin">Prov. 31.10.</note> 
               <hi>Her Children ariſe up and call
her bleſſed, her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band alſo, and he praiſeth her.</hi> We alſo
have read of the conſtancy of a <hi>Ruth,</hi> of <hi>Sarah</hi> and
<hi>Rebecka's</hi> fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to their Husbands; and in the <hi>Roman</hi>
Government, the Bride uſed <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98231:25"/> to ſalute her Husband:
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi tu Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>ego ſemper
Caia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was an excellent Character the Holy Ghoſt gives of
<hi>Abigal,</hi> that ſhe was a Woman of an excellent Underſtanding, in
Pacifying <hi>David,</hi> and ſaving her houſe. <hi>Phile</hi> and
<hi>Zenobia</hi> were exceeding Lovers of their Husbands; and what Lamps of
Female Glory were the <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi>'s, <hi>Panthia</hi>'s,
<hi>Porcia</hi>'s, and others! and how great an Admiration had that
<hi>Perſian</hi> Lady for her Husband, when at <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Wedding,
ſhe was asked, How ſhe lik'd the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom; I know not, ſaid ſhe, for
I ſaw none there, but mine own Husband. And <hi>Plutarch</hi> relates of the
Love and Wiſdom of the <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Women, that when their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands
were involved in a Civil War, by the endeavours and Solicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their
Wives, a Peace was made, and for their Honour and Reward they were admitted to
the Council. And it was one of the Articles made with <hi>Hannibal,</hi> That
if the <hi>Cartha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inians</hi> had
any contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with the <hi>Celtians,</hi> it ſhould <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98231:25"/> be decided by the <hi>Celtian</hi> Women; and we find a paſſage
in <hi>Euripides</hi> to this effect, 
<q> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Optima viri poſſeſſio uxor benevola,</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mittigans iram, &amp; avertens animum ejus à
triſtitia.</hi>
                  </l> 
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <l>Mans beſt poſſeſſion is a loving Wife,</l> 
                  <l>She tempers anger and diverts all ſtrife.</l> 
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And as in this Conjugal affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is ſuch an egreſs
and expanſion of the Heart and Spirits to the object loved, and a Love and
reſpect of that extent, that an <hi>Ovid</hi> can't teach it, nor
<hi>Solomon</hi> deſcribe, nor <hi>Apelles</hi> paint it; ſo an high care
and ſolicitation for the well-being and preſervation of each other:<note place="margin">
                  <p>Res eſt ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciti plena timoris a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor.</p> 
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ovids E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> as the Poet well
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the jealouſie of <hi>Penelope</hi> for the ſafety of
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes,</hi> 
               <q> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>In te fingebam violentes Troias ituros,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ovids E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nomine in Hectureo, pallida ſemper eram.</hi>
                  </l> 
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98231:26"/> 
                  <l>How oft my dear <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> did I ſee</l> 
                  <l>In my ſad thoughts proud <hi>Trojans</hi> ruſh on
thee,</l> 
                  <l>And when great <hi>Hectors</hi> but touch'd mine ears,</l> 
                  <l>My cheeks drew paleneſs from my paler fears.</l> 
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And as abſence is tedious and unpleaſant, ſo their departure
each from other afflictive and uneaſie: When <hi>Thais</hi> took her leave of
<hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> 
               <q> 
                  <l>—<hi>Egone quid velim,</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Noctes dieſque ames me, me deſideres,</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Me ſomnies, me expectes, me cogites,</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Me ſperes, me te oblectes, mecum tota ſis,</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meus ſac poſtremo animus, quando ego ſum
tuus.</hi>
                  </l> 
               </q>
               <q> 
                  <l>Doeſt ask, my Dear, what ſervice I will have,</l> 
                  <l>To love me day and night is all I crave;</l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98231:26"/>To dream on me, to expect, to think on
me,</l> 
                  <l>Depend and hope, ſtill covet me to ſee;</l> 
                  <l>Delight thy ſelf in me, be wholly mine,</l> 
                  <l>For know, my Love, that I am wholly thine.</l> 
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But we muſt ſhake off this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Argument, for there's
no end of it. In ſhort, how have Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Hiſtorians and Poets
cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated this Alliance, this Conjugal Oeconomy; this Divine conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!
<hi>Dies deficeret &amp; Nox;</hi> we will only give you the rapture of
<hi>Boae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>O Faelix hominum genus!</l> 
               <l>Si veſtros ammos Amor</l> 
               <l>Quo Caelo regitur, regat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now two being become one by this Myſterious Conjunction, they
reciprocally love and mutually af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect each other, and jointly promote the
happineſs of both: the man is obliged to love his Wife, as <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98231:27"/> ſayes,<note place="margin">Dilectione ſincera,
caſtâ &amp; perpetuâ, &amp; exemplo ſanctae vitae uxoribus
praebeat. Spontaneâ nempè vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate, ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcentes ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem
Dei qui id etiam an te peccatum conſtituit.</note> with a chaſte and
conſtant love, and ſet their Wives the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a Religious Life: And
the Woman to love, reverence and ſubmit to her Husband, freely and chearfully
acknowledging the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God from the beginning, as <hi>Zanchius</hi>
directs. And as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial honour is to be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved inviolable, ſo
the Holy Ghoſt is pleaſed to repreſent the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Union between
Chriſt and his Church, by the ſemblance and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Marriage.<note place="margin">Quo ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re videtur, ſequens com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratio, de Chriſto
ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiamſuam ſanctifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. <hi>Eſtius</hi> in loc. <hi>Ariſtotle
Pol.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Love and Affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proper to Mankind, is called
<hi>Amor cognitionis. Leon Hebreus</hi> calls it Rational love, whereby all the
Affections and Actions are confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the Object; and this Love the
Philoſopher ſtyles, <hi>Debitum Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> a Debt we owe to Nature, and
the neglect thereof a treſpaſs againſt Nature; becauſe God is Love it
ſelf; he made the World out of Love, and wonderfully illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated this Love
in redeeming of it; and the Emanations of it are viſible in his Divine
Providence, <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98231:27"/> and in his care and protection of every
individual, and particle of the Creation.</p>
            <q> 
               <l>
                  <hi>Si rerum quaeris fuerit quis finis &amp; ortus,</hi>
               </l> 
               <l>
                  <hi>Deſine, nam cauſa eſt unica ſolus Amor.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q> 
               <l>Doeſt ask the reaſon moved God above</l> 
               <l>To make the world, the only cauſe was Love.</l> 
            </q>
            <p>And here we might enter into a vaſt and Philoſophical Field of
diſcourſe,<note place="margin">Amor eſt voluntatis affectus. Forma eſt
vitalis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ex ipſo bono ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans par I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas. <hi>Plato.</hi>
Pulchritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do eſt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiti, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruente or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,
men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurá &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um conſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens.</note> and give you
the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diviſion and object of Love; according to <hi>Leon
Hebreus,</hi> a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary affection and deſire to enjoy that which was good:
<hi>Omne pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum eſt amabile;</hi> and the more fair the object, the more
deſirable. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> defines Beauty, a reſulting from effaſed good.
Others call it a perfection of the whole compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this Comelineſs
is called Grace, which joyned with Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is like the Shinings that come 
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98231:28"/> from a Glorious and Divine Sun; than which admirable
Beauty, ſays <hi>Socrates,</hi> there is nothing ſo maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, nothing
ſo ſacred, divine and Lovely, and nothing can charm mankind ſo much. When
<hi>Xerxes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all the Temples of the <hi>Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Deities,
he cauſed the Picture of <hi>Diana, in Integrum ſervari,</hi> to be
ſpared for its Beauty and Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty:<note place="margin">Naturae gaudentis
opus.</note> But how much more charming is natural Beauty, which <hi>Plato</hi>
calls the Quinteſſence and Triumph of Nature. <hi>Carneades</hi> calls it,
Still Rethorick, that perſwades without Speech; 'tis a Kingdom without a
Militia;<note place="margin">Gratior eſt pulchro, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens è cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore
virtus. <hi>Vir. Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ads.</hi>
               </note> which made <hi>Diogenes</hi> call
Beautiful Women Queens, becauſe all were willing to obey their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: and
the Poet deſcribes <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi>'s aſtoniſhment when ſhe firſt
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held <hi>Aeneas,</hi> 
               <q>Obſtupuit primo aſpectu Sydonia Dido.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> was tranſported with the Beauty
of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Origen.</note> he was <hi>Fairer than the Sons
of men. Joſeph</hi>'s comelineſs conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liated <pb n="41" facs="tcp:98231:28"/> his
Favour in the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Court:<note place="margin">Lib. de pul. Jeſ.
&amp; Mar.</note> How much doth <hi>P. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rales</hi> admire the Beauty and
Luſtre of the Virgin <hi>Mary! Anthony</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> and
<hi>Theſeus</hi> was charmed with <hi>Hellena.</hi> And though the Mind is
not occaſioned by the Body, yet Philoſophy tells us it follows the
temperament of it; and where the external Qualities are ſo beautiful, we may
gueſs at the Judgment, concluding that the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſitions of the
Soul quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and animates the outward Graces; and there being ſo ſtrong
a love between the Body and Soul, we may from thence preſume of a
ſimilitude in the Qualities of the Soul, with thoſe lovely impreſſions
of nature we find in the Body.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Leon Hebreus</hi> divides Love into three parts, Natural,
Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and Rational: Natural Love is ſeen in the Elements, Sun, Moon
and Stars, in Mettals and Stones; <hi>gravia tendunt deorſum;</hi> Fire
upwards, and in Vegetables, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Senſible Love in brute Beaſts, for
the preſervation of the Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; <pb n="42" facs="tcp:98231:29"/> and Rational, which
was hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before, as proper to Mankind; but then only reſpecting
<hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropy,</hi> the love of men to their own Species; whereas the
affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men are likewiſe dilated on things as well as perſons. We
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire Virtue, Wiſdom, Eloquence, Profit, Wealth, Honour, Beauty,
Friendſhip, Charity, and other things, Arts and Sciences; but we only name
them, each head would take up a copious diſcourſe by it ſelf. And
pleading <hi>Peccavi</hi> for this pleaſant digreſſion, we return to
proſecute the remaining Effects of Marriage: And the next is Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>When he ſees thoſe fine and ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate pieces of himſelf,
whom God hath graciouſly given him, how does he adore the Divine Goodneſs
that made him a Father, and Inſtrument to preſerve by a continued
Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion Gods Church in the World! and how is he obliged to give down to
his Off-ſpring thoſe Precepts and Inſtitutes for Gods glory, their good
and advantage, he received <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98231:29"/> from his Anceſtors! Children
are the bleſſing of their Parents, and a good Parent a bleſſing to his
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. When God bleſſed our firſt Parents, 'twas thus: <hi>Be
fruitful,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 1.28.</hi> Signifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at ſecundita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem omnem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,
&amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam, &amp; quae Deus illis omnia laeta, &amp; pauſta pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus
fuit. <hi>Paulus Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius, in Locum. Gen. 22.17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and multiply,
and repleniſh the earth;</hi> which Bleſſing, as a learned man tells us,
ſignifies all Fruitfulneſs, Favour and Plenty; and that God would heap on
them all Joys and Proſperity: ſo that the bleſſing of Children and all
other Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are annext to Marriage. So when God bleſſed <hi>Abraham;
In bleſſing I will bleſs thee, and in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying I will multiply thy
ſeed as the Stars in Heaven, and as the ſand on the Sea-ſhore, and thy
ſeed ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Gate of his Enemies:</hi> The words are an
Hebraiſm, <hi>verbalia addita verbis;</hi> which ſignifies Gods earneſt
reſolutions to Bleſs <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and his Seed after him: The
<hi>Hebrews</hi> obſerved a Conveniency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the forms of expreſſion
and the thing expreſt: So when Chriſt ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke
22.</hi> Cordis &amp; Oris oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem notat.</note> 
               <hi>With deſire I have
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; Aquinas</hi> noteth on the place, that the Heart and Tongue both 
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98231:30"/> Prayed: And <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth the goodneſs
of God to the Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 105.6, 8, 9,
10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>O ye ſeed of Abraham his Servant, and ye ſeed of Jacob
his Choſen, he hath remembred his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for ever; the word which he
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to a Thouſand Generations; which Covenant he made unto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,
and his Oath unto Iſaac, and confirmed the ſame unto Jacob for a Law, and
to Iſrael for an everlaſting Covenant, ſaying, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee will I give
the land of Canaan, the lot of your Inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when God bleſſed <hi>Jacob, I will pour my Spirit on thy
ſeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 44.3.</note> 
               <hi>and my bleſſing on
thine Off-ſpring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as theſe are the Promiſes and Bleſſings of God on the
one hand, ſo 'tis the Parents Duty on the other to expreſs their
Obligations and Thankfulneſs in the Education and Care of their
Children;<note place="margin">Prov 20.3.</note> like <hi>Solomon's Juſt
man,</hi> who <hi>walketh in his Integrity, and his Children are bleſſed
after him.</hi> How does he conſult all wayes and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods to make his
Children tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy! By Integrity we may <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98231:30"/> underſtand
that faithfulneſs a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oweth to his Children, in giving them a religious
and ſober Education: Nurture is as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for Children as
Nouriſhment, which if Parents neglect, they are <hi>Peremtores potius quam
parentes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qûo ſemel eſt imbuta recens
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabit odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem teſta diu. <hi>Prov. 22.6.</hi>
               </note> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paricides
than Parents: but the good Father takes <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Advice, and trains
up his Child in the way he ſhould goe; and with that wiſe <hi>Spartan</hi>
Prince, when he was asked what he ſhould teach his Children, made
Anſwer,<note place="margin">Ageſilaus.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Xenoph.</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe things that they
ſhould make uſe of when they became men:</hi> For Youth is like ſoft
Wax,<note place="margin">Tanquam abraſa ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula.</note> takes any
Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; therefore it ought to be ſeaſon'd with Religion and
Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; as the Spring is the fitteſt ſeed-time for Grain and Planting,
ſo Youth is the moſt convenient ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſcatter the Seeds of
Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge upon the ground of the mind.</p>
            <p>And this Integrity alſo takes in the good Example of the Parent,
for good Examples are very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent with Children. It is record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98231:31"/> for the honour of <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuentur quod fecit Jupiter quam quid docuit
<hi>Plato.</hi>
               </note> that he took care of his Children, and 'twas his good
reſolution, That he and his Houſe would ſerve the Lord: <hi>Lycurgus</hi>
commanded all his Citizens to dine publickly, where their Children heard no
idle Speech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but grave diſcourſe about the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the
Common-wealth. The good Parent is an utter Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to evil Cuſtoms, he well
knows what arguments are brought from thence to ſupport ill actions; for
Cuſtome (as the Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> calls it) is the dumb Idol of the
world,<note place="margin">Idolum Theatri.</note> the great Mart of Error,
wherein Men unthriftily take up on truſt, and at laſt break by too much
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying on the bankrupt ſecurity of a Faſhion; the <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi>
and blaze men play about, as Flies about a Candle, 'till they burn their wings:
He will therefore be ſure to give his Children a good Example, and aboliſh
bad Cuſtomes. <hi>Virgil</hi> brings in <hi>Aeneas</hi> adviſing his Son
<hi>Aſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius;</hi> 
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 12.</note>
                     <hi>Diſce puer virtutem ex
me, veroſque labores.</hi>
                  </l> 
                  <l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98231:31"/>Virtue and Patience learn of me, my
Son.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>Homer</hi> repreſents <hi>Hector</hi> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his
Son; 
<q>
                  <l>Let it be ſaid, here's a good Son indeed,</l> 
                  <l>That did his noble Father far exceed.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And if Heathens profeſt this ſort of Piety, how much more
ſhould Chriſtian Parents bring up their Children in the Admonition, and
Fear of the Lord! How much was it to the honour and glory of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
when God gives this Teſtimony of him! <hi>For I know him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.19</note> 
               <hi>that he will command his Children, and his
Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, and do
ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Judgment, that the Lord may bring upon Abraham that which he
hath ſpoken of him.</hi> Which was, that in him ſhould all the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of
the Earth be bleſſed; As if God ſhould argue, How ſhall I ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill my
promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> unleſs <hi>Abraham</hi> inſtruct his
Children? and <pb n="48" facs="tcp:98231:32"/> what Parent will Wilfully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his
own and Childrens hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs?<note place="margin">1 Kings 2.2, 3.</note> So
<hi>David</hi> charged <hi>Solomon: Be thou ſtrong therefore, and ſhew thy
ſelf a man: And keep the charge of the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, to
keep his Statutes, his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his Teſtimonies, as it is written in
the Law of Moſes:</hi> and that he might the rather embrace his charge, he
adds the reaſon, <hi>that thou maiſt proſper in all thou
doeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Majori ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitudine me parturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebat Spiritu
quam pepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat carne, parturiebat carne ut in hanc tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerer corde
ut in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam lucem re naſcerer. <hi>Aug. Lib. 2.</hi> confeſ. <hi>ch.
3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and whitherſoever thou turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy ſelf:</hi> And St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> reports of his Mother <hi>Monica,</hi> that ſhe ceaſed
not do her endeavours eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, that he might be truly religious, and as well
Gods Child by Grace as hers by Nature. This is that Domeſtick care that is
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on all Parents, to teach their Children their Duty to God himſelf,
to Honour their Parents, to reverence their Superiours, be courteous to their
Equals, and that in all their Actions, they ſhould have <hi>Oculi in
Metam,</hi> and ſo be <hi>recti in curiâ:</hi> the Wiſe-man alſo
tells us, what Inſtructions he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98231:32"/> from his
Parents:<note place="margin">Prov. 4.</note> To ſtudy Wiſdom and to ſhun
the path of the Wicked; and further tells us, that <hi>whoſo loveth Wiſdom
rejoyceth his Father;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 29.</note> and this
Wiſdom is the fear of the Lord, as we find after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: <hi>The fear of the
Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>that is Wiſdom, and the
Knowledge of the Holy is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good Parent well conſiders Religion as moſt eſſential
to his Childrens Happineſs; that in the end of their days, when all other
things fail, then God may be the ſtrength of their Heart, and their Portion
for ever.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Antiſtes Sacrorum,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Dr.
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> uſed prayer in his Family four times a day, and on
<hi>Frydays</hi> Cathechized them; as remembring that charge, which God
commanded the old <hi>Iſraelites, Theſe Words which I command thee this
day, ſhall be in thine Heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6.6, 7.</note>
               <hi>And thou ſhalt teach them diligently to thy Children, and thou ſhalt
talk of of them when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt
by the way, and when thou lieſt down, and when thou <pb n="50" facs="tcp:98231:33"/>
riſeſt up.</hi> And next after Religion his care is manifeſt, to learn
them Arts and Sciences, knowing that Ignorance brings Idleneſs, Idleneſs
brings ill Company, which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil uſeth as an Engine to Dethrone men from
the ſafe and honourable ſeat of Virtue to the precipice of ruine and
deſtruction, and ſo enchanting their Underſtanding, their Miſery
attends them <hi>incognito;</hi> whereas good and wiſe Aſſociates are our
ſecond Genius to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;<note place="margin">Phil. de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines. <hi>Ab.
34.</hi>
               </note> or as another expreſſeth it, 'Tis an Indication of a good
and virtuous diſpoſition, to chooſe learned and virtuous Companions:
which made <hi>Alexander</hi> ſo highly eſteem <hi>Ariſtotle,
Themiſtocles</hi> his <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> his
<hi>Canutius.</hi> And he recommends virtue to them, as the complement of a
happy life, and only Immortal thing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Mortality, and
repreſents it to them with ſuch Beauty and Majeſty, that it muſt needs
conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate Love and Veneration; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Charm ſo powerful, the
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Soul admires it, as the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98231:33"/> and Queen of an
Intellectual Beauty.</p>
            <p>He well knows that Nature has, as it were, of purpoſe left many
things for Art and Induſtry to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and make up; and as 'tis Arts duty
to imitate Nature, ſo 'tis its dignity to perfect it: Nature gives in the
Oar, but Induſtry refines it into Silver. God hath beſtowed on his Children
the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Underſtanding of a Reaſonable Being, and
though by Original Sin this Light be eclipſed, this Underſtanding and
Reaſon wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd, there is the more need of ſupernatural accompliſhments.
Arts and Sciences poliſh and improve Nature, and confer a great help and
furtherance thereunto, and cure the diſeaſes of our Minds: as it was ſaid
of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture brought forth one
<hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> and Learning another, his Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals were ſo
improved by his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. He recommends therefore to his Children the ſtudy
of the Scriptures and practical Divinity, commends the devotion of a
<hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> 
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:98231:34"/> the Juſtice of an <hi>Ariſtides,</hi>
the good Laws of a <hi>Solon,</hi> the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a <hi>Cato,</hi> the
Courage of a <hi>Scipio,</hi> the Moderation of a <hi>Fabius,</hi> and the
publick Spirit of a <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro;</hi> and commends Learning, that is the only
thing to enrich their minds with ſuch precious furniture, that
<hi>Alexander</hi> profeſs'd he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excell in Wiſdom than Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
and as that which promotes the civil end of our Life: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t in honore cum
dignitate vivamus;</hi> and that a man without Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is like the
Beaſts that periſh: therefore he is highly ſollicitous to inſtruct his
Children, with the Emanations of Divine Wiſdom, the <hi>Ideas</hi> of
Morality, the Simples of Science, the Flowers of Retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, Reaſon and
Philoſophy, and to build them up into the Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Perfection of men.
How does he ſet before them, that Learning was the Glory of <hi>Scipia
Affricanus, Charles</hi> the Great, <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Veſpatian, Charles</hi> the
fifth, and our late King <hi>James!</hi> and how much Hiſtorians, Poets and
Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers <pb n="53" facs="tcp:98231:34"/> have celebrated the Glories of the
Learned; and by this ſtir up the genius of his own Children to an Emulation
of their virtues. And we read of great Perſonages that taught their Children
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> read <hi>Cicero</hi> and
<hi>Virgil</hi> to his Children, and of a <hi>Grecian</hi> Emperour, that
taught his Daughter himſelf: and Biſhop <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> cites her in his
Apology, as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of a Church Hiſtory: ſo <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi>
inſtructed his Children in the Latin and Greek Tongues: And Sir <hi>Tho.
Moor</hi> when Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour taught his three Daughters, and
<hi>Buchanal</hi> relates of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Learning of Sir <hi>Anthony
Cooks</hi> Children, inſtructed by their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And as theſe things are incumbent on Parents, ſo 'tis the
Childrens happineſs to have ſuch Watches over them: having touched at the
Juſt mans Integrity, the Wiſe man adds this, His <hi>Children are
bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed after him.</hi> 'Tis indeed a great bleſſing to Children, to
have Wiſe and Religious Parents; and when <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98231:35"/> they ſit at
the feet of ſuch <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliels,</hi> they enjoy that Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Queen
of <hi>Sheba</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Servants,<note place="margin">1 Kings 10.8.</note> 
               <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are thy Men, happy are theſe thy
Servants, that ſtand continually before thee, and hear thy Wiſdom.</hi> And
as a grateful acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Obligations, they ought to give their
Parents all Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Honour and Reverence. 'Tis the Apoſtles exhortation,
<hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother, this is the firſt commandment with
Promiſe:</hi> And whats that? <hi>That thy days may be long in the Land.</hi>
And this promiſe were ſufficient if all duty were ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeded. And the
wiſe man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts us, <hi>Honour thy Father that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat thee, and deſpiſe
not thy Mother when old:</hi> And indeed the Book of <hi>Proverbs</hi> is full
of ghoſtly advice to Children; and 'tis but common gratitude, to be thankful
to them who gave them being, and by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in Religion and Learning
they give them alſo well-being; with what ardent affection and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
ought they to anſwer the <pb n="55" facs="tcp:98231:35"/> expectations of their Parents,
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Apoſtles exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;<note place="margin">Col.
3.20.</note> 
               <hi>Children obey your Parents in all things, for this is well
pleaſing to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we will paſs on to proſecute our further diſcourſe;
only let us hear <hi>Plato's</hi> opinion about the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Youth: In
the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Youth, ſays he, well ordered and taught, conſiſts the
flouriſhing of a Common-wealth. And indeed he is altogether in the right; for
the Education and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Youth, is like the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring and poliſhing
Stones and Utenſils for ſome magnificent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick: And here we could wiſh
eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Family a little Seminary of Religion and Learning, for the ſervice of
Church and State; as our Univerſities are for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of
Perſons for Sacred and Civil Offices: And we find <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> of the
ſame Judgment; and tells us, that Education and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reform the Life and
Manners, and afford the beſt advice for the Government of a Common-wealth: 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98231:36"/> And we thence inferr, that a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Life and Manners,
not only produce an Excellent Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy and Inſtitution of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but
are the moſt ſerviceable and adventitious helps to preſerve the Unity and
Beauty of ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, and infallibly annex Happineſs and
Proſperity to ſuch a People.</p>
            <p>And if good Government and Diſcipline were obſerved in
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, how much would it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to publick advantage? As in an Army, what
glorious encounters are they ſit for, when the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral underſtands his
Intereſt and Station, and all his Souldiers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly underſtand their
Poſts, all expert and acute in Military un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings. So in a State, when
all are ſit to rule, and all willing to obey their Prince;<note place="margin">Imperatoris faelicitas in ſubditorum faelicitate conſiſtat.
<hi>Grotius. Lipſ. Polit.</hi>
               </note> whoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs conſiſts in
the happineſs of his People, as <hi>Grotius</hi> tells us; and
<hi>Lipſius</hi> calls it, <hi>Verum &amp; legitimum Imperium:</hi> A true
and lawful Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire ſo governed. Now when the People are taught to be
religious, <pb n="57" facs="tcp:98231:36"/> Religion muſt needs flouriſh; and when they
are inſtructed in Arts and Sciences, Trades and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, it muſt needs
conduce to their happineſs, profit, honour and greatneſs.</p>
            <p>We all know, that thoſe States thrived beſt, that were moſt
addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſervice of their Gods: <hi>Rome</hi> ſaw her beſt dayes
when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion flouriſht there under a <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Auguſtus, Titus,
Conſtantine, Theodoſius,</hi> and others: And <hi>Bodin</hi> gives us the
reaſons of it;<note place="margin">Ab câ enim ſubditorum fides in
Principes obedientia erga Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtratus pietas in Parentes, charitas in
ſingulos, &amp; juſtititia in omnes pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. <hi>Lib.
7.</hi>
               </note> From hence, ſays he, they became Loyal to their Prince,
Obedient to the Magiſtrate, Dutiful to Parents, Charitable to all, with an
equal diſtribution of Juſtice: and by theſe adminiſtrations they
exceeded other Nations, as <hi>Martial</hi> ſets them out.</p>
            <q> 
               <l>
                  <hi>Terrarum Dea, gentiumque Roma,</hi>
               </l> 
               <l>
                  <hi>Cui par eſt nihil, &amp; nihil ſecundum.</hi>
               </l> 
            </q>
            <q> 
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> of all Nations is the Lady Queen,</l> 
               <l>To which the like, or ſecond, is not ſeen.</l> 
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98231:37"/>
               <note place="margin">Hac enim ſola Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na
gens to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum orbem ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>git. <hi>Bodin.</hi>
               </note>They exceeding other Nations in Piety, as
one obſerves; by this they conquered all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. And St.
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tells us, that Princes without learning and the fear
of God, manage but lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their greateſt Affairs, and are blind in
diſcretion and knowledge: The Piety of an <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> brought him
both Honour and Succeſs; the Devotion of a <hi>Numa</hi> and a
<hi>Fabius,</hi> made them formidable and glorious: And we have read of a Law
of one of our <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings, that at the Aſſizes the Biſhop was
obliged to accompany the Judge, that the one might countenance Gods Law, and
the other Mans; in Imitation of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> who ſent the
<hi>Levites</hi> with his Princes,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 17.6.</note> to
teach in the Cities of <hi>Judah.</hi> We paſs over the Piety of
<hi>Charles</hi> the great, who uſed to ſet his Crown on the Bible; of
<hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who when the Bible was
preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her by the Citizens of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> kiſs'd it, and laid
it to her <pb n="59" facs="tcp:98231:37"/> Breaſts: and the Examples of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are of
great force to promote Devotion in the People. <hi>Regis ad Exemplum,</hi> was
a ſaying of old, and all Ages have confirmed it.</p>
            <p>Now when Religion is ſettled, it produces peace and a general
hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, which produceth peaceable Society, the Improvement of Arts and
Sciences, Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and on theſe depend the happineſs of a
State. We paſs over the ſad effects of War and Hoſtility, of Rapine and
Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and all thoſe <hi>Evertores horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici,</hi> thoſe
Devaſtations which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed it. How are Temples and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities razed to
the ground, and Religion ſpuriated into Hereſie and Schiſm; all which
ceaſe, by reaſon the cauſe is taken away, and the State preſerved from
Forreign In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions and Civil Diſſenſions.</p>
            <p>Here we may ſee how things are chained and linkt together, and
how naturally effects flow from their cauſes; and how Family-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
where the Father go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns his Children, and they again <pb n="60" facs="tcp:98231:38"/>
obey their Parents, bears ſo ſtrict an Analogy and ſemblance between a
Prince and his People; and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily-government, a little Model and pattern of
National Diſcipline, which was erected firſt from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
Adminiſtrations: For 'till <hi>Nimrod</hi>'s time, who Erected the firſt
Monarchy National, <hi>Noah</hi> and his Generations, as <hi>Paraeus</hi> tells
us,<note place="margin">Par fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Paraeus in
Gen.</hi>
               </note> did rule gently by their Families.</p>
            <p>But in Proceſs of time the World growing exceeding Populous,
thô the ſeveral Families of the Earth did, and doe retain their
Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, and firſt Preſcriptions for their particular Order and Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;
they are ſince Politically uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and a whole Land or Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under an
Uniformity of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and as it were ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of Families
incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into one Body, for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Strength and Preſervation. Here
the Sagacity of Man under the Divine Conduct is very viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">Vis unita f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tim.
<hi>Lord</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con<hi>'s Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſays.</hi>
               </note> all Eſtates
ſubſcribe to Unity, as the Mother and Foundation of <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98231:38"/>
Concord and Preſervation; and by this Polity, not only Sacred and Civil
Rights are preſerved, but ſettled and confirmed; and <hi>Nimrod</hi> was
the firſt Proſecutor hereof, and changed the Paternal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into
National Monarchy; and the Genius of his aſpiring Nature inſtructed him in
this principle of Policy; which very word is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Greek
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to Sell, whence <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a City, and
metony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mically taken to ſignifie Commerce and Trade in a Society of men,
which did enſue, and was in the greateſt meaſure augmented by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
Government. Now this <hi>Nimrod</hi> in Scripture is ſtyled a mighty
Hunter:<note place="margin">Viribus ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtis, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretus. <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatus in loc.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Toſtatus</hi>
ſpeaks of him, being ſtrong in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and Diſcreet in mind, by the Engine
of his Wit, and Art of Gratification, and by heaping good turns on Injured
Perſons, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage a multitude to his Party,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minandi Occaſionem na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius,
reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m obtulit. <hi>Muſcul. in
loc.</hi>
               </note> by whoſe aſſiſtance he purſued men as a Hunter does
Beaſts: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſayes <hi>Muſculus,</hi> he obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Kingdom by
his Valour and <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98231:39"/> Victory, the rude and barbarous People
being reduced to Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;<note place="margin">Muſculus, <hi>St.</hi>
Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Cornelius a Lapide, Mercer <hi>and</hi> Rivet <hi>in
Locum.</hi>
               </note> which Conqueſt by moſt Commentators is aſcribed to the
Vigour of his Body, and Virtue of his Mind; ſurpaſſing others by his
Humanity and Benignity, he got together a Party, whereby he ſubdued his
Oppoſites, and ſettled his Government.</p>
            <p>But ſince it hath been the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Policy of ſucceeding Ages,
by Marriage and Affinity to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate that in their Families, which he only
obtained by Craft and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty; witneſs the Royal Families of the World ever
ſince, a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and Superiority having been generally
ſucceſſive;<note place="margin">Moſes, Joſhua, Samuel,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> (except only when it pleaſed God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire and
adapt ſome particular men for the Government of his People in the Primitive
times.) And thus Marriage hath not only Intailed Soveraignty on their
Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, but alſo ſettled the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peace, Trade and Commerce of one
Nation and State with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; hath promoted Alliances <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98231:39"/> of
common preſervations, againſt the Enemies of Gods Church; and whereby
ſeveral Countreys have enjoyed the Commodities and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures of each
other, for a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual good and advantage. <hi>Solomon</hi> Married
<hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter, and ſettled a Trade and Commerce with the
<hi>Aegyptians.</hi> What recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> to <hi>Cyrus</hi>
but Marriage? what reconciled the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines</hi> to the <hi>Romans?</hi>
Marriage; they were Enemies and Friends both in one days time,<note place="margin">Salubrem providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.</hi>
               </note> which
<hi>Seneca</hi> ſtyles an healing Providence. What reconciled <hi>Pompey</hi>
and <hi>Caeſar</hi> after ſo much Fighting and Blood-ſhed, but Marriage?
Which way did <hi>Alexander</hi> reconcile and allye <hi>Aſia</hi> to
<hi>Europe,</hi> but by Marriage? And our Politick <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh
Marrying the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Heir of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi>
ingrafted the white Roſe on the Red, and ſo put a Period to thoſe Civil
Diſſentions which had cauſed ſo much Blood-ſhed; and by Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of
his two Daughters, entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Heirs to the <hi>French</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98231:40"/> and Crown of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And in ſhort, the
Soveraign Houſes of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> being a Kin to each other by
Marriage, the Peace of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> and other parts have been
preſerved thereby;<note place="margin">Firmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Imperii munimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,
<hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus an.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> calls it the moſt ſtrong
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative of Empire.</p>
            <p>And if theſe Obligations were but duly obſerved by Nations and
Families, what Halcion dayes would be found on Earth! this Contract of Mankind
ſhould be like that Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Chain which reaches from Earth to Heaven,
preſerving the mutual coherence of the Elements, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all things are
reciprocally ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, and make this lower World like the Imperial
Heavens; where all the motions of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending Orbs, the ſeveral
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tions, the various
poſition of the Stars and Planets produce a raviſhing Chorus, and an
Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny truly beautiful: And what peace and quiet too, as the Emanations of
this ſacred Friendſhip, would be eſtabliſhed! and what a ſeries of
<hi>Hacentia's,</hi> and pleaſing Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations <pb n="65" facs="tcp:98231:40"/> ſlow
from it! 'twould lead us up to the <hi>via Lactea,</hi> and uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er us with
Muſick to the preſence of Divinity.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken ſomething of the Illuſtrious Effects of
Marriage, we proceed to inquire what method we are to take to render it
bleſſed, propitious and ſatisfactory, which brings us to peruſe the
Prayer of <hi>Eliezer,</hi> for conſtituting a Family; in which Government
was firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and if ſtill preſerved, is the beſt means to
preſerve Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Diſcipline, which was deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 24.</hi> v. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>And he ſaid, O Lord God of my Maſter Abraham, I pray thee
ſend me good ſpeed this day, and ſhew kindneſs unto my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
Abraham.</p>
               </q>
               <p>THe words contain a pathetical Prayer of <hi>Eliezer,
Abraham</hi>'s Servant, for a good Wife for his <pb n="66" facs="tcp:98231:41"/> Maſters
Son, <hi>I pray thee,</hi> &amp;c. The Context and preceding Verſes give us
an account of <hi>Abrahams</hi> directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>Eliezer</hi>'s entrance on
this deſign; here we find <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant begining with his
Supplication to the Lord God of his Maſter <hi>Abraham,</hi> for ſucceſs
in this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking. The Explication being ſo obvious, we only take notice
of four particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Solemn Addreſs to God for ſucceſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Prayer is ſtrengthened by this Expreſſion,
<hi>O Lord God of my Maſter Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Object and Deſign of his Prayer, to have <hi>good
ſucceſs this Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That particular kindneſs God would vouchſafe unto
<hi>Abraham,</hi> in the conceſſion and gratification of his requeſt,
<hi>And ſhew kindneſs unto my Maſter Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Firſt</hi> of the Firſt of theſe,
<hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. His Solemn Addreſs to God for Succeſs; this is
<hi>Eliezer</hi>'s me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and as the beſt way and <pb n="67" facs="tcp:98231:41"/>
means to accompliſh his deſires, is to addreſs himſelf to God, who is
the Author and giver of every good thing: He, and He only can give ſucceſs
to our Undertakings, or blaſt and diſappoint our moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
Deſigns and Intentions: Prayer is a Duty which keeps the trade of Religion a
going, and 'tis our happineſs that God puts it into our hearts to Pray; which
is no other than a religious Speech, directed to God after a due ſort,
concerning things appertaining to his glory and our good; and it is the Key of
Heaven, and Conduit of Mercy, a Perfume and ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in Gods Noſtrils,
and the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of the Soul to the Throne of Grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Damaſcen</hi> tells,<note place="margin">De Orth. Fid.
lib.</note> that in Prayer the Will is filled with deſire, and the deſires
flame and blaze upwards to God; and though Prayer is an act of the Will, yet it
hath its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in the Heart, and is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Soul, like the
ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits to the Body.</p>
               <p>It is, and hath been the Method <pb n="68" facs="tcp:98231:42"/> and Uſage
of Gods Servants in all Ages, to Pray to God on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.<note place="margin">Gen. 13.4.</note> Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> for <hi>Iſhmael,</hi>
and when he removed his Family to <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> he
built an Altar, and <hi>Called on the Name of the Lord:</hi> And <hi>David</hi>
after he had ſettled the Ark, returned to bleſs his Houſe, that is, to
Pray for his People: ſo good <hi>Nehemiah, Firſt I Prayed unto the Lord,
and then I ſpake unto the King:</hi> And 'tis the Apoſtles Exhortation,
<hi>In all things, by Prayer and Supplication, let your requeſts be made
known unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. His Prayer is ſtrengthened by this Expreſſion,
<hi>O Lord God of my Maſter Abraham:</hi> 'Tis very Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, and gives us
to underſtand Gods great affections to his emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Servants, and the ſeed
of the Faithful: And this place more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly refers to Gods promiſe to
<hi>Abraham</hi> concerning <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen.
19.17.</note> and 'tis very probable this was a great Topick with <hi>Eliezer,
Iſaac</hi> being the Son of the Promiſe; and ſuch forms of Invocation
were very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in thoſe times: in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <pb n="69" facs="tcp:98231:42"/>
charge to his Servant,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 7.</note> he
encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges him in his undertaking, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting Gods Promiſes to his
Seed.</p>
               <p>And we find often times in Gods appearance to his Servants, he
is pleaſed to expreſs himſelf as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring his Promiſes: when he
appeared to <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 26.24</note> 
                  <hi>I am the
God of thy Father, fear not;</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> when afraid of
<hi>Eſau,</hi> ſtrengthened himſelf by this Invocation,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.9.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord God of my father Abraham, and God of
my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iſaac, the Lord which ſaid unto me, I will deal well with
thee.</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> would not
believe him,<note place="margin">Exo. 4.5.</note> but God to confirm his Faith
and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> was pleaſed to work Miracles; <hi>That they
may believe</hi> (ſays God) <hi>that the God of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the God of
Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob, hath appeared unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Object and Deſign of his Prayer, To have <hi>Good
ſpeed this day:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fac ut ſe mihi oſſert quod peto.
<hi>Zenochius in Locum.</hi>
                  </note> Good ſpeed is an indefinite wiſh, and
refers to ſeveral Objects; but here particularly ſignifies, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in
chooſing a good Wife for his Maſters Son; and ſome render 
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98231:43"/> it, That <hi>he might obtain what he asked;</hi> others,
<hi>That what he deſired might be proſperous and
ſucceſſeful.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Proſperum fac mihi occurſum.
<hi>Vatablus in Locum.</hi>
                  </note> Both which are Synominous; and 'tis very
aptly and ſignificantly rendred, <hi>Good ſpeed;</hi> becauſe the
chooſing and enjoying a good Wife is ſo eſſential a part of a mans
happineſs: this prompted <hi>Abraham</hi> to that wonderful care in ſeeking
out a good Wife for his Son;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 3.</note> and
nothing could be more ſatisfactory to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> than the enjoyment of
this bleſſing: <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſeven years ſeemed but a few dayes, for
the Love he bare unto <hi>Rachel.</hi> And all Ages of the World have
ſubſcribed to this Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That particular Kindneſs God would vouchſafe unto
<hi>Abraham;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fac miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat non alio
jure fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum hoc au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire, niſi qua Deus gratiam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Abramae pollitius
fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhew Kindneſs unto my Maſter Abraham.</hi> We are
here to enquire what kindneſs the accompliſhment hereof would be unto
<hi>Abraham.</hi> And nothing can pleaſe better, and be more acceptable to a
Father, than to ſee his Son happy in a good Wife: A noter on the place well
expreſſeth himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:98231:43"/>And a Father that hath taken ſo much care
and pains in the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and bringing up of his Son, who is ſo dear to
him; and to whom he hath given ſo good an Example, when his Son is well
married, and his Father ſees him proſecuting thoſe admirable
Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he received from him; and with the help of a good Wife, how
does he eſteem himſelf hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in his Sons happineſs; whoſe Wiſdom and
conduct may render even his Poſterity happy! To which the Wiſe man
alludes,<note place="margin">Pro. 24.23.</note> 
                  <hi>The Father of the Righteous
ſhall greatly rejoice, and he that begetteth a wiſe Child, ſhall have joy
of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſpoken ſomething by way of Explication, we paſs on
to the Obſervations, and each con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with a ſhort Inference.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prayer is a great and Indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Duty.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerv. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A Tribute we owe in recogniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Divine Soveraignty; 'tis
the Juſt Prerogative God may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <pb n="72" facs="tcp:98231:44"/> from his Creatures:
The other parts and pieces of the Creation purſue the deſign of their
beings; the Sacred Poet tells us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.1.</note>
                  <hi>The Heavens declare Gods Glory,</hi> the Sun rules the Day, and the Moon
the Night; the Elements obſerve their appointed Stations, the Earth is
Lowermoſt, the Sea keeps his bounds, the Air, <hi>Aethur,</hi> and
<hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraethur</hi> obſerve their Sphaerical apartments; the Earth is our
Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, the Beaſt of the Field our Food, Vegetables afford both Medicine
and Nouriſhment, and all things admirably uſeful, and adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the
ſervice of man.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no
ſpeech nor language, where their Voice is not heard: Their line is gone
throughout all the Earth, and their words to the end of the World.</hi> And are
wonderful <hi>Indiciums</hi> of Gods Glory and goodneſs in their ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
man; and ſhall he only dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and prove Anomalous and Sceptical? ſhall
the beſt piece of the Creation prove the worſt, and unſerviceable? The
nobleſt beings ſhew moſt Beauty in their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <pb n="73" facs="tcp:98231:44"/> and ſhall man that was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to admire the Wiſdom and
goodneſs of his Maker, be ſilent, and do leſs than the dumb pieces of the
Creation? God forbid.</p>
               <p>The all-wiſe God hath commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated the ſenſible and
eminent influences of his mercy, goodneſs, and bounty, to the rational
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man; that ſo Body and Soul jointly engaged, might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce an
harmony of Praiſe and Thankſgiving to the great Creator of the World:
wherefore did God give him his Tongue, the Organ of Speech, but to pray unto
his Maker; and with <hi>David, O Lord open thou my Lips, and my Mouth ſhall
ſhew forth thy Praiſe?</hi> God gave him his hands to lift them up in
prayer to him,<note place="margin">Tendens ad ſydera pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</note> and with
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that his Prayer might <hi>come before him as Incenſe, and
the lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his hands as the Evening Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So alſo the Inorganical parts are <pb n="74" facs="tcp:98231:45"/> to be
chiefly imployed in our prayers to God,<note place="margin">Elevatio mentis ad
Deum.</note> the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Will and Affections, without which prayer is
inſignificant; 'tis only the ſpiritual and fervent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that availeth,
which is called <hi>wraſtling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 32.24. <hi>Oratio
eſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cax.</hi> Beza.</note> and <hi>pouring</hi> out of the <hi>Soul</hi>
to <hi>God;</hi> and 'tis that which is our indiſpenſible Duty; all the
faculties of the Soul muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged herein, to ſupplicate and adore the
great God, and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally with <hi>David;</hi> exciting all within us to
pray unto that God who gave us our Being, and to Praiſe him for all our
Mercies and Benefits:<note place="margin">Affectus operi nomen impoſuit.
<hi>St. Ambroſ.</hi>
                  </note> for 'tis the lively affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Soul in a
Duty that gives it a Name, and makes it ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful: ſo <hi>Eliezer</hi>
here pray'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for his Maſters Son. And prayer is our Duty, to ſhew
our dependance on God; <hi>In him we live, move, and have our Being;</hi> our
daily exigencies invite us to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Inf.</note>Let us therefore pray daily, for 
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98231:45"/> prayer is as uſeful to us, as our daily bread; and we
are encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged hereto, for he filleth the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with good things; and
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to pray without ceaſing: In all things let your Requeſts and
Supplications be made known to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſome forms of Invocation and phraſeologies, are
very prevalent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerv. 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Eliezer</hi> here, <hi>O Lord God of my Maſter
Abraham;</hi> and this expreſſion is uſed to ſtrengthen
<hi>Eliezers</hi> Faith. And we may learn from hence; That upon particular
wants and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, we ought to uſe ſuch Phraſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologies, which are
<hi>analogous</hi> to Gods Promiſes, or referr to our wants: Thus
<hi>Joſhua,</hi> after <hi>Iſrael</hi> had ſinn'd:<note place="margin">Joſh. 7.8, 9</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord, what ſhall I ſay, when
Iſrael turneth their backs before their Enemies?</hi> That was when they were
purſued by the men of <hi>Ai;</hi> which implies his earneſt
Expoſtulation with God to preſerve his own People, and concludes with this
prevailing <pb n="76" facs="tcp:98231:46"/> argument; <hi>And what wilt thou do unto thy
great Name?</hi> The Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> exhorts the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce in theſe Expreſſions their former Sins.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Take with you words, and turn to the
Lord, and ſay unto him, Take away all Iniquity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us graciouſly;
ſo will we render the calves of our Lips. Aſhur ſhall not ſave us, we
will not ride upon Horſes, neither will we ſay any more to the work of our
hands, ye are our Gods, for with thee the Fatherleſs find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Mercy.</hi> So
<hi>Elijah</hi> prayed unto God,<note place="margin">1 Kings 17.20.</note>
                  <hi>Haſt thou alſo brought evil up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Widdow with whom I ſojourn, by
ſlaying her Son?</hi> Which is as if he remembred God, who commanded him to
go to that Widdow for ſuccour, as we find in the beginning of that Chapter:
And we read of <hi>Aſa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 14.14.</note> when he
went to Battle, he uſed this pathetical way of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf to
God: <hi>Help us, O Lord our God, for we reſt in thee, and in thy Name we go
againſt this Multitude: O Lord, thou art our God, let not man prevail
againſt thee:</hi> and <pb n="77" facs="tcp:98231:46"/> ſo <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> when
the Army of the <hi>Heathens</hi> were coming againſt him, he prayed unto
God.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord God of our Fathers,
art thou not God in Heaven? and ruleſt not thou over all the Kingdoms of the
Heathen? and in thine hand is there not power and might, ſo that none is able
to withſtand thee? Art thou not our God, who didſt drive out the
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Land before thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſrael, and gaveſt it to the
ſeed of Abraham thy Friend for ever?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, In our Thanskgiving and Exultation, we ſhould admire
and paraphraſe on Gods power, ſuitable to the Nature of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance:
ſuch was the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> after the Children of
<hi>Iſraels</hi> deliverance at the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtical
Triumph repeating the manner of their deliverance and <hi>Pharaohs</hi>
overthrow; what pious Airs and Encomiums was chanted out by the thankful
<hi>Iſraelites!</hi> And what was <hi>Deborahs</hi> Song, but the ſlaming
Raptures of a rejoicing <pb n="78" facs="tcp:98231:47"/> Heart? And the twenty ſecond of
<hi>Samuel,</hi> is a continued thankſgiving of <hi>David</hi> to God for his
mercies; and the 105, and 106. <hi>Pſalms,</hi> are a Hiſtory of the
deliverance of Gods People, and <hi>Davids</hi> thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Gods
Mercies.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Inf.</note>Let us therefore remember the
advice of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.18.</note> 
                  <hi>In
every thing give thanks, for this is the Will of God in Jeſus Christ
concerning you:</hi> And as we expect any bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, we muſt pray for
them; ſo alſo to improve what we have with thankfulneſs is the only way
to have more.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerv. 3.</note>
                  <hi>That we ought to pray
for each other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Here was good <hi>Eliezer</hi> praying for his
Maſters Son; and 'tis the Duty of Chriſtians to aſſiſt each other
with their Prayers. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle bids us make Supplication for all Saints,
and the Apoſtle pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thoſe that had not ſeen his 
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98231:47"/> Face in the Fleſh; and how paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate was he for
the prayers of of the People! and conjures them, <hi>For Chriſts
ſake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and the love of the
Spirit, that they ſhould ſtrive with him in their Prayers to God for him.
Tertullian</hi> calls it,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.30.</note> An holy
conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy to beſiege Heaven: this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction in Prayer edifies the
whole Church, the Communion of Saints, and is of advantage to every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;
nay, even the wicked have a ſenſe, and need of the Prayers of good men:
ſo <hi>Pharaoh</hi> told <hi>Moſes, Intreat the Lord your God to turn away
this death only:</hi> That is, pray unto God for me; and the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Saints
are very acceptable: God would not hear <hi>Job's</hi> Friends,<note place="margin">Job 42.8.</note> but ſays God, <hi>My ſervant Job ſhall pray
for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This praying for one another does not terminate in
perſonal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, but comprehends pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Chriſts Church and
Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for the Propagation of his Goſpel, that God would <hi>give him 
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98231:48"/> the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the utmoſt part of
the World for his Poſſeſſion:</hi> and how pathetically did the
<hi>Jews</hi> in Captivity expreſs their zeal for the welfare of
<hi>Jeruſalem! By the Rivers of Babilon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal.
137.</note> 
                  <hi>there we ſat down, yea we wept when we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Zion;</hi>
and ſo to the end! and for Nations, it is St. <hi>Pauls</hi>
exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>That firſt of all,
Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſions and giving of thanks be made for all
men: For Kings and all that are in Authority, that we may lead quiet and
peaceable lives, in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> Nay further, we are
commanded to pray for our Enemies,<note place="margin">Mat. 5 44.</note> and
Chriſt prayed for them that crucified him,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.34 Acts
7.60.</note> 
                  <hi>Father forgive them;</hi> and that <hi>Protomartyr</hi> St.
<hi>Step<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> prayed for them that
ſtoned him. And 'tis the noble and heroick deſign of a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Heart, to
be ſerviceable to Church and State, by prayer, either to depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
Judgments, or obtain Mercies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To deprecate Judgements. How did <hi>Abraham</hi>
intercede with <pb n="81" facs="tcp:98231:48"/> God for <hi>Sodom!</hi> and God was
pleaſed to anſwer him,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.32.</note> 
                  <hi>That if ten
righteous were in it, he would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it for tens ſake!</hi> And how
Gracious was God to <hi>Jeruſalem! And I ſought for a man among
them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek 22.30.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſhould make up the
Hedge, and ſtand in the gap before me, for the Land, that I ſhould not
deſtroy it, but I found none:</hi> It implies Gods great reſpect for the
righteous; which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſtyles <hi>fundamentum ſeculi,</hi> an
everlaſting Foundation: publick Spirited Perſons are like Pillars, to bear
up Gods Wrath from the place they live in.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To obtain Mercies; ſo <hi>Elijah</hi> prayed for Rain
in the days of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and obtained it, after three years
Intermiſſion; and ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> that great Maſter in
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> after God had reveal'd his will to him, he cryed unto God
for the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and could bid them <hi>Stand ſtill
and ſee the Salvation of God;</hi> and we all know what a glorious Victory
followed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:98231:49"/>
                  <note place="margin">Inf.</note>Let us
therefore upon the whole, Pray for each other, Gods Church and People, that by
the fervency and continuance of our Prayers, we may either ſtand in the gap
with <hi>Abraham,</hi> or prevail with <hi>Jacob;</hi> at leaſt be found
among the righteous, that when Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are in the earth, God may ſay
unto us as he did to <hi>Noah, Come thou and all thine houſe into the
Ark,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 7.1.</note> 
                  <hi>for thee have I ſeen
righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before me in this generation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerv. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Prayer is the only way
to obtain Mercies, or divert Judgments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How great Priviledge is it to be admitted into the Preſence of
ſome great Monarch! but how much greater Prerogative hath the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout
Chriſtian, that by fervent Prayers, and ardent effuſion of his Tears and
Wiſhes, may freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr with the King of Kings! this penetrates the
Clouds and Sphears, and mounts us to the boſome of <pb n="83" facs="tcp:98231:49"/> the
great Benefactor; and a Charm that if rightly performed, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails on
Omnipotency;<note place="margin">Oratio pura coelos pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trans va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cua non
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibit. <hi>St. Auſtin.</hi>
                  </note> this Dove ſent to Heaven, often
brings an Olive-leaf in his Mouth: This fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Prayer (ſayes St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi>) as it pierceth Heaven, ſo it will not return without
effect. And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Duty, but our daily wants put us upon this
undertaking; we are helpleſs Creatures of our ſelves, and Prayer is our
only refuge; there is an admirable Oeconomy in the Divine Wiſdome, to bring
man to his Duty and Happineſs; God tells us,<note place="margin">Ezek.
36.37.</note> That <hi>for this he will be enquired of by the Houſe of
Iſrael, to do this for them:</hi> And 'tis but highly rational to confeſs
our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon him that gave us being. The Kingly Prophet ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly
deſcribes Gods goodneſs to thoſe that call upon him in 145<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  <hi>Pſalm,</hi> from the begining to the the end: And certainly 'tis no
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that is not worth ſeeking to God for; but when ſought and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained,
it makes the bleſſing the <pb n="84" facs="tcp:98231:50"/> more acceptable, and obliges
us to improve it, with the greater thankfulneſs and ſobriety: we can never
loſe any thing by prayer, for we are never out of Gods reach to relieve us;
if God pleaſe to anſwer us, the Bleſſing is the more ſafe and
ſweet, and if deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed we are the more humble, and patient, and content that
God ſhould be Maſter of his own boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>We have the Practice of Gods People recommended to our
Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and the admirable effects of their Prayers recorded for our
encouragement: here good <hi>Eliezer</hi> prayes unto God for <hi>good
ſpeed;</hi> he would not venture on it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Petitioning the Lord God of
his Maſter <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the good ſucceſs he met with, was the
ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Prayers. <hi>Abraham</hi> tells him God would ſend his Angel
before him, and proſper his way; which implies the ſtrength of
<hi>Abraham's</hi> Faith; and his Servant, after he <pb n="85" facs="tcp:98231:50"/> had
prayed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 13, 14.</note> in the very next
<hi>verſes</hi> gives us a kind of Prophetick hint of what would come to
paſs, and reſigns himſelf up to the conduct of Providence; <hi>Behold I
ſtand here by the Well of Water;</hi> and ſo on:<note place="margin">Non
tentat Deum cujus inſtinctu ad hoc motus fuerat. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius in
loc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Junius</hi> obſerveth, he did not tempt God, becauſe
God prompted him hereto; for ſuch manuductory paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Providence are
but Preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary to ſucceſs, and antecede the effects of our Prayers:<note place="margin">Signum quod ſtatuit congruum fuiſſe, erat, enim ſigna
bonae uxoris &amp; indolis affabilis, hoſpitalis &amp; ſtrenuae qualem
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verat pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citurum &amp; Iſaaco &amp; Abrahamo. <hi>St. Chryſ. in
loc.</hi>
                  </note> And St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> well obſerves, The ſign,
ſayes he, which <hi>Eliezer</hi> pitcht up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was very agreeable; for thoſe
things, as affability and courteſie, are the indications of a good Wife, and
ſuch as would pleaſe <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> alludes to ſuch antecedent Providences: ſayes
God, <hi>I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct thee, and teach thee in the way which thou ſhalt
go, and I will guide thee with mine Eye;</hi> and ſuch gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious dealings of
God with his People are our great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the effects of Prayer's 
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98231:51"/> miraculous;<note place="margin">James 5.17.</note> as if
<hi>Elijah</hi> could ſhut and open Heaven at his pleaſure. <hi>Jacobs</hi>
Prayer turned away the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and Wrath of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and his four
hundred men: after <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> had cried to the Lord for the Children of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were drowned in the
<hi>Red-Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after <hi>David</hi> had prayed unto his God,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.37.</note> 
                  <hi>That delivered him out of the paw of the
Lyon and the bear, he alſo delivered him out of the hands of the
Philiſtine:</hi> And when <hi>Elijah</hi> prayes unto God, <hi>That the meal
ſhall not waſte, nor the cruiſe of Oyl fail, till the day that God ſend
Rain on Earth:</hi> And when <hi>Hezekiah</hi> prayed againſt
<hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi> for reproaching the living God, the Lord was pleaſed to
anſwer him,<note place="margin">2 King 19.</note> that he ſhould not ſhoot
one Arrow, nor come before the City with Shields or Bucklers, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn as he
came; and God ſmote a hundred fourſcore and five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> and even <hi>Sennacherib</hi> himſelf ſlain by his
two Sons: And let but thoſe three Servants of <pb n="87" facs="tcp:98231:51"/> that God
whom they truſted would deliver them, but pray to him in the fiery Furnace;
though the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heat ſlay even thoſe that put them in, yet a hair of their
heads ſhall not be ſinged, nor ſhall <hi>their Coats be
changed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> neither <hi>the ſmell of Fire
paſs on them.:</hi> Nay, even the Son of God ſhall bear them Company and
preſerve them. And when <hi>Daniel</hi> is in the Den of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, God
anſwers his Prayers, and ſends his Angel and ſhuts the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mouths,
that they could not hurt him. In fine, by Prayer the Moon hath ſtood ſtill,
the Sun gone backward, the Ravens have brought Food, the Heavens rained Manna,
the Rocks afforded Water, the Fire hath given over Burning, the Lyons have
ſtopt their Mouths,<note place="margin">Fidelibus totus mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus diviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum
eſt. <hi>St. Auſtin de Civ. Dei.</hi>
                  </note> and all Creatures ſhall
muſter up themſelves to defend the Body of Chriſt; whereupon ſayes St.
<hi>Auſtin,</hi> The Saints have all the World at their ſervice: And gives
us the Reaſon, <hi>Domine quis tenet te?</hi> Lord, ſayes he, who can hold
thee? who <pb n="88" facs="tcp:98231:52"/> can fetter and reſtrain Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy?</p>
               <p>Nay, even <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> have alwaies had
a great venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Prayer, which is a reproach to Chriſtians, to be
out-done by them. <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> thought it ſufficient for his
ſafety, he could anſwer,<note place="margin">At ego rem Divinam facio.</note>
                  <hi>But I nm about the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of my Gods:</hi> And 'twas the Heathen
Cuſtom, not to venture upon buſineſs of moment without the Invocation of
their Gods: And the advice of <hi>Xenophon</hi> was Divine, That in
Proſperity they ſhould worſhip their Gods, that when they had a more
particular need of their aſſiſtance they might with greater confidence
approach them at their Altars, commending the ſucceſs to the Power and
Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thoſe Deities they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>Publius Scipio</hi> uſed
alwayes to go to the <hi>Capitol</hi> before he went to the Senate, and ſo
begin the ſervice of the Commonwealth with prayer, as <hi>Suetonius</hi>
tells us<note n="†" place="margin">Benè ac ſapienter Majores
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituerunt ut rerum agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daram ita dicendi ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium à
prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationibus capere. <hi>Sueto. in vit. Caeſ.</hi>
                  </note>: 
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98231:52"/> It was the Wiſdom of thoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments to commence
all their buſineſs with the ſervice of their Gods.</p>
               <p>Let us Chriſtians therefore,<note place="margin">Inf.</note>
that have the Son of God to intercede for us (he is the Angel ſtanding before
the Throne with the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cenſer in his hand,<note place="margin">Rev.
8.3.</note> filled with the Odours of his Merits,<note place="margin">Ipſe
ſolus eſt cujus gratia De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi>
                  </note>
to offer up with our prayers) be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to come to the Throne of Grace, to
find Mercy and Grace to help in time of need: <hi>For he is able to ſave to
the uttermoſt all that come unto God by him.</hi> Let us come to God in all
Conditions. In our Adverſity, God tells us, <hi>No good thing will he
withhold from them that diligently ſeek him:</hi> Prayer liſts us in the
ſervice of the Almighty, and inrolls us under the Divine Standard, and from
whence we may expect the favourable Protections of Providence.</p>
               <p>And in our Proſperity, leſt we <pb n="90" facs="tcp:98231:53"/> be full
and deny God, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Corrective the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours met
with in the midſt of their Triumph and Glory; Look behind thee,<note place="margin">Reſpice poſt te &amp; homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento te.
<hi>Suetonius.</hi>
                  </note> and conſider thou alſo art mortal, and ſubject
to miſery; for we know not to what extremities we may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. Let us
therefore pray with <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 71.12.</note>
                  <hi>O Lord be not far from me, O God make haſte for my help:</hi> And if we
expect good ſucceſs in our Prayers, let us be alwayes deeply affected with
thoſe things we pray for.<note place="margin">St. Matth. 22.11.</note> It is
ſaid, <hi>The King came in to ſee the Gueſts;</hi> ſo in Prayer, the
King of Glory looks into the frame and diſpoſition of our Hearts; let us
therefore uſe Prayer aright, that it prime our Souls, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us in
the Oyl of Grace from Wind and Weather.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerv. 5.</note>
                  <hi>Gods bleſſing and
providing for Children, is a great bleſſing to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Jacob</hi> tells us, Children are the 
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98231:53"/> Gift of God; when he met his Brother he told him,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe are the Children God hath
graciouſly given me;</hi> and his great care and affection to his Children,
is a great Pattern to Parents: Now Children being the ſame Fleſh, and
pieces of their Parents, their Affection to them muſt needs be very great,
and be highly ſolicitous to promote their welfare; as our Saviours Parents at
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did preſent him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord for his Bleſſing:
And we cannot give it you <hi>in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> for Speech is lame, and words
cannot reach the ſence of the thing ſignified; but moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly when
God is pleaſed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Prayers of Parents, and bleſs and provide
for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, it is a very great kindneſs and Mercy to Parents: We
will give you <hi>Davids</hi> ſence of this matter; when Gods Promiſe was
made known to <hi>David:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>And
when thy dayes ſhall be fulfill'd, and thou ſhalt ſleep with thy Fathers,
I will ſet up thy ſeed after thee, which ſhall <pb n="92" facs="tcp:98231:54"/>
proceed out of thy Bowels, and I will eſtabliſh his Kingdom:</hi> And we
have <hi>Davids</hi> acknowledgment in the following verſes, <hi>Who am I, O
Lord God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and what is my
Houſe, that thou haſt brought me hitherto! and this was yet a ſmall thing
in thy ſight, O Lord God, for thou haſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken alſo of thy Servants
Houſe, for a great while to come, and is this the manner of man, O Lord
God!</hi> Nay in the 20. <hi>verſe,</hi> he wants words to expreſs his
thankfulneſs; <hi>And what can David ſay more unto thee? for thou, Lord
God, knoweſt thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant:</hi> And when God had placed <hi>Solomon</hi> upon
the Throne, he breaks out into this <hi>Elogium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings
1.48.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, which hath given me
one to ſit upon the Throne this day, mine eyes even ſeeing it.</hi> Thus
the admirable care <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> took for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and his great
charge to <hi>Eliezer,</hi> is an aſſured In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of his great Love and
Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and that it would pleaſe God to anſwer <hi>Eliezers</hi>
requeſt, he uſeth this Expreſſion; <hi>And ſhew <pb n="93" facs="tcp:98231:54"/>
kindneſs unto my Maſter Abraham:</hi> And how did the Heart of old
<hi>Jacob</hi> revive, when he heard of <hi>Joſephs</hi> being alive! how did
he contemplate and adore the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Providence, That God had ſo
miraculouſly preſerved and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for him; and made him Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour over
all the Land of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt!</hi> and when he met him, how was he overwhelmed
with Joy!<note place="margin">Gen. 46.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Now let me die,</hi> ſayes
he, <hi>ſince I have ſeen thy Face, and thou art yet alive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As 'tis a great mercy to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to ſee their
Children bleſt and provided for, ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, undutiful Children
are a great trouble and grief to their Parents. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us,
<hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Fool hath no Joy;</hi> that is, hath a great deal of
Trouble and Affliction: the words are a <hi>Meioſis,</hi> there is more
intended than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd. How bitterly did <hi>David</hi> mourn, when
<hi>Tamar</hi> was raviſhed, <hi>Amnon</hi> kill'd, and <hi>Abſalom</hi>
caught <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98231:55"/> by the Hair of his Head and ſlain! And we meet
with <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> that had fooliſh and wicked Children, wiſhing
that either he had lived ſingle,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam ut caelebs
vix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſem, aut orbus peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſem.</note> or dyed Childleſs. 'Tis ſad
indeed to bring forth Children to the Murtherer, the Devil: and how miſerably
does the Mother in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> warble out her mournful ditty; <hi>Quo
pueri eſtis profecti!</hi> Poor Souls, what's become of you!</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Inf.</note>Let Parents therefore carefully
inſtruct their Children, and be thankful for the Bleſſings God
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes on them; and let Children be dutiful to their Parents, and let both
obſerve <hi>Davids</hi> experience he found of both:<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.25</note> 
                  <hi>I have not ſeen the Righteous
forſaken, nor his Seed begging Bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obſerv. 6. <hi>and
laſt.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>How happy are the Saints, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions,
they may pray to God to ſanctifie mercies!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſaid of the Cherubims, that <hi>there were hands under
their wings;</hi> 
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98231:55"/> to ſignifie, that where there is that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight of Knowledge, there ſhould
be hands to put that light into practice: And our Saviour tells us, <hi>If ye
know theſe things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 13.3.</note> 
                  <hi>happy are ye
if ye do them;</hi> ſo that Happineſs
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pronounced of practice, and not
ſpeculation; and here conſiſts the Saints Happineſs, that they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
their knowledge by prayer and walking with God: And by This the Wiſe man
tells us, they <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>btain favour of
the Lord;</hi> that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s
<hi>Mercer</hi> gloſſeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id vult quod à
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trat.</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. Matth. 7.7.</note> They have as it
were what they pleaſe of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd
are ſure of Gods favour and protection in all caſes, and the promiſes of
God on their ſide. <hi>Ask and it ſhall be given you, ſeek
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ye ſhall find, knock and it
ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e opened unto you;</hi> and
nothing can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtrain Omnipotency
but Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ief.</p>
               <p>Now, 'tis as true in Divinity as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Philoſophy, That Knowledge
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Power is to no effect, unleſs
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t be produced into Act; for the 
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98231:56"/> end of Knowledge is Action;<note place="margin">Fruſtra
eſt potentia quae nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducitur in actum. <hi>Ariſt.</hi>
Eth.</note> as if Arts and Sciences: And ſhall their Votaries improve
themſelves by all the advantages and benefits of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; nay, an Heathen
affirm, That felicity conſiſteth not in the <hi>Theory,</hi> but in the
practice of moral Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; and tell the world, that the naked knowledge
without the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Virtue, is like thoſe that ask advice of the
Phyſician about bodily diſtempers, but will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuffer any remedy to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred? And ſhall
the Servants o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God be ſatisfied
with the <hi>Ideas</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Truth
floating in their Brains, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out an influence on the Heart and Life? No, the
devout Chriſtian la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours with as much more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs, as his End and
Reward is a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bove others; he does not ſatisfie himſelf with Speculation or
Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, bare obſervance will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſe him; he is altogether fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reality and performance, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a deeper inſight into Divine my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteries than other men: he
wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowes, that 'tis not thoſe
tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:98231:56"/> know
only,<note place="margin">James 1.21.</note> but thoſe that do the will of God,
who ſhall enter into the Kingdom of his Father, as Chriſt tells us.</p>
               <p>Moſt admirable is the advice of <hi>Eliphaz</hi> to
<hi>Job:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 5. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> A wiſe man
labours to know the goodneſs of every thing; and here lyes the happineſs of
the Saints above other People, even in Creature-enjoyments, that by Prayer both
Mercies and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſanctified to them; others in their enjoyments
ſuck in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing as well as the
Honey, 'tis the good Chriſtian only that feeds on clean and polite
Pleaſure: others are miſled into corrupt apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and
preſumptions of things, the Saints only preſerve their Intellectuals
untainted; others in the midſt of their abundance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute their
Affections, due only to God, to a corruptible Creature; the Saints only improve
their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and enjoyments to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as they are the emanations of 
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98231:57"/> his bounty, and make the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſerviceable to
illuſtrate and ſet forward the accumulated glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Creator: others
take up their reſt, and place their <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Bonum</hi> in the enjoyments
of this world, and eſteem it their only Joy when their Oyl and Wine
increaſeth: there is ſuch Corruption in their Nature, and Sophiſtry in
the Creature, that from the greatneſs of their wealth, they conclude they
have much laid up for many years,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.</note> they may
take their eaſe, eat, drink and be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;<note place="margin">Pſal.
49.11.</note> and the Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>Their inward thought is, that
their Houſes ſhall endure for ever, and their dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places to all
generations;</hi> and even Deifie themſelves in the reflection of their own
grandeur.<note place="margin">Pſal 49.14.</note> Alas! they are aſleep in
their Tent of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiſm and Senſuality, and little think that a day of
viſitation and recompenſe for ſin is at hand; and on a ſuddain
mortality overtakes them, as <hi>David</hi> tells us, <hi>Like ſheep 
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98231:57"/> they are laid in the grave, death ſhall feed on them,
and the upright ſhall have dominion over them in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and their
beauty ſhall conſume in the grave from their dwelling.</hi> Then is their
miſtaken happineſs come to a final period, and their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry commenced
ETERNAL; then their Cuts and Complements will appear nothing elſe but
affected Vanities, their Pride and Luxury, their Swaggering and their
Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, their Formula's of Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance and Courtſhip ſhall then be
pronounced but glittering Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: Then Apoſtles and Saints ſhall
ſhine in Glory, when the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting <hi>Nero</hi>'s of the World ſhall
be thrown to Hell: And at laſt be forced to confeſs, <hi>We Fools counted
their Life madneſs, and their end to have been without Honour: How are they
now rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned amongſt the Saints, and have their Portion with the
Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:98231:58"/>But the Devour Chriſtian hath <hi>Oculus
in metam,</hi> his eye on the Mark, and ſteers all his actions by the
Compaſs of Gods Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; he uſes
the Creatures with a critical frui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, and as helps only, not <hi>Remora</hi>'s in his paſſage to
the New <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and by Prayer endeavours to reduce the Creature
to it's primitive goodneſs, that ſo the Curſe being ſubducted, he may
enjoy them with a bleſſing; as the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Every Creature
of God is good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſanctified by the Word of God and prayer:</hi> By
which the Creature is ſanctified theſe three wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In obtaining Mercies: We ought to ſeek to God, as
<hi>Eliezer</hi> did; and ſo the Apoſtle exhorts us: <hi>In all things with
Prayer and Supplication, let your requeſts be made known to God:</hi> And we
have the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and God expects that we
ſhould acknowledge his Dominion and Power over ſecond Agents.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98231:58"/>2. Prayer ſanctifies the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and uſe of them. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>To re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ice in our labour is the Gift of God:</hi> pleaſure is
in it ſelf lawful, but corrupt Nature is apt to make us Love pleaſure more
than God, therefore we ought to pray againſt its prevalency: And our Tables
too often are turned into a Snare; we muſt pray there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to uſe the
Creature with that temperance and ſobriety, as may raiſe us nearer to God
in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the Divine Providence, and care over us, and as Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of Gods Love towards us, without which worldly abundance may prove but a
deceitful argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods favour; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Afflictions have proved
the diſſembled favours of Affection.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Prayer ſanctifies the Creature, in the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>membrance and Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of Gods Mercies in them, and with
Thankfulneſs to improve thoſe <pb n="102" facs="tcp:98231:59"/> Diſpenſations of
Grace and Favour: Thus did the Holy Pſalmiſt.<note place="margin">Pſal.
23.5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou prepareſt a Table for me in the preſence of mine
Enemies, thou anointeſt my Head with Oyl, my cup runneth over: Surely
goodneſs and mercy ſhall follow me all the daies of my Life, and I will
dwell in the houſe of the Lord for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:59"/>
            <head>Books lately printed for <hi>John Salusbury</hi> at the
<hi>Atlas</hi> in <hi>Cornhill</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>OEconomica Sacra:</hi> Or, a Parae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netical Diſcourſe of
Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; together with ſome particular Remarks on the Marriage of
<hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecka.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iter ad Aſtra:</hi> Or, The Portray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Suffering
Chriſtian; with an Introduction of Mans Creation. By the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>Of Contentment, Patience and Reſignation to the Will of God: In
ſeveral Sermons. By <hi>Iſaac Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> D. D. Never before Printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Neceſſarium:</hi> Or, Chriſt's Juſtification of
<hi>Mary</hi>'s Choice, and of his Servants wrongfully Accuſed: Containing a
Reſolution of many weighty Caſes of Conſcience. <hi>Viz.</hi> Indifferent
Things, Obedience to the Higher Powers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With ſome
Reflections on Popery, and a brief Account of the many Cruelties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by
the Papiſts. By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98231:60"/>A Second Volume of Diſcourſes: By <hi>Hezekiah
Burton,</hi> D. D. late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Barns</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> and
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendary of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The true Prophecies or Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtications of <hi>Michael
Noſtradamus,</hi> Phyſician to <hi>Henr</hi> 2. <hi>Francis</hi> 2. and
<hi>Charles</hi> 9. Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and one of the beſt
Aſtronomers that ever were. A Work full of Curioſity and Learning.
Tranſlated and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by <hi>Theophilus de Garenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res,</hi> Doctor in Phyſick <hi>Colleg. Lond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fifteen Comforts of Raſh and Inconſiderate Marriage, or
Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions upon the Miſcarriages of a Wedded Eſtate: With the
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of three Comforts more.</p>
            <p>The Secret Hiſtory of the moſt Renowned Queen
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> By a Perſon of
Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>The Laws and Acts of Parliament made by King <hi>James</hi> I. and
his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Succeſſors, Kings of <hi>Scotland.</hi> In <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:60"/>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:98231:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:98231:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:98231:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:98231:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:98231:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:98231:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:98231:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:98231:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:98231:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:98231:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:98231:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:98231:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:98231:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:98231:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98231:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98231:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:98231:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:98231:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:98231:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:98231:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:98231:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98231:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:98231:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:98231:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
